<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An ansvvere to a sermon preached the 17 of April anno D. 1608, by George Downame Doctour of Divinitie and intituled, A sermon defendinge the honorable function of bishops wherein; all his reasons, brought to prove the honorable function of our L. Bishops, to be of divine institution; are answered and refuted.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1609</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 124 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10320</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20605</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115514</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850733</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850733</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15958</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10320)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15958)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1002:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An ansvvere to a sermon preached the 17 of April anno D. 1608, by George Downame Doctour of Divinitie and intituled, A sermon defendinge the honorable function of bishops wherein; all his reasons, brought to prove the honorable function of our L. Bishops, to be of divine institution; are answered and refuted.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>58, [2]; 166 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted [by Jodocus Hondius and Giles Thorp],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Amsterdam] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>anno 1609.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Misattributed to John Rainolds. MS note by James Kennedy on copy in New College, Edinburgh, ascribes to a "Sheerwood", which, says S. B. Burbage (1962) may be Richard Sherwood--Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing, 3rd ed. (1980).</note>
                  <note>A reply to Downame's "A sermon defending the honourable function of bishops" (part 2 of his "Two sermons").</note>
                  <note>Hondius printed the first part; Thorp printed part 2 (STC).</note>
                  <note>"Mr Downames sermon preached at Lambith, Aprill 17. 1608. Answered and refuted" (caption title) begins new pagination and register.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Downame, George, d. 1634. --  Two sermons --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Bishops --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Episcopacy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15958:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15958:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSVVERE TO A SERMON PREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHED <hi>THE 17 OF APRIL ANNO D.</hi> 1608, <hi>BY GEORGE DOW<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NAME DOCTO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R OF DIVI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NITIE AND INTITVLED,</hi> A ſermon defendinge the honorable function of Biſhops; wherein, All his reaſons, brought to prove the honorable function of our L. Biſhops, to be of divine inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution; are anſwered and refuted.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Prov. <hi>8.6.7.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Giue eare, for I vvill ſpeake of excellent things; &amp; the openinge of my lippes, shall teach things that be right.</p>
               <p>For my mouth ſhall ſpeak the truthe; &amp; my lippes abhorre wickednes.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Imprinted anno 1609.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:15958:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:15958:2"/>
            <head>To the Christian reader</head>
            <p>CHRISTIAN reader, when I had peruſed this ſermon made by M. Downame, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the honorable function of Bbs, as he ſaith, &amp; ſawe that it tended directly to prove, that the Caling of our L. Bbs. (as they now ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe it in the Church of England) is not onely <hi>lavvfull &amp; good;</hi> but alſo to be holden, <hi>jure diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no;</hi> not as an humane ordinance, their ancient &amp; wonted tenure, but by devine right, as the verie &amp; ymediate ordinance of Chriſt: I deemed it as needfull to be anſwered, as any book our Oppoſites have at any time ſett forth. For how ever M. D. affirmeth the doctrine therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined, <hi>to be not onely true, but a profitable &amp; neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie truth,</hi> and that in the judgment of all men, which are <hi>not partiall &amp; full of preiudice:</hi> it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that it is a doctrine vtterlie falſe, verie hurtfull &amp; obnoxius, neceſſarie in deed, to be confuted, at no hand to be beleeued: doctrine, repugnant to the truth, the word of the truth, ſcripture of truth, contrarie to the judgment and practyce, of the prime Churches next after
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15958:3"/>Chriſt &amp; his Apoſtles; &amp; of all reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, ſince the reſtabliſhinge of the goſpell by the worthyes in theſe later
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liff, Huſſe, Luther, Zuin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>glius, &amp;c.</note> times: Againſt the doctrine of our ymediate forefathers, (ſome of whom were worthy Martyrs,)
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Latimer, Cramner &amp;c</note> who in their ſubmiſſion to K. H. the 8. at the aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of the Popes authoritie out of England, acknowledge with ſubſcription,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">See the whole ſtory in the acts &amp; monuments &amp; in the book called the Bbs. kook,</note> that the diſparitie of Miniſters and Lordly premacie of Bbs, was but a politik device of the Fathers, not any ordinance of Chriſt Ieſus:
<note place="margin">&amp; Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat legum Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticarum, tit. de divi nis officijs. ca. 10. 11.</note> and that the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Churche by the Miniſter and certeine Seniours or Eldes in everie pariſhe, was the ancient diſcipline: a doctrine, I ſaie, cleane contrary to the profeſſed judgment of all our worthy writers,
<note n="(d)" place="margin">Whita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, Fulk, &amp;c.</note> who in their anſweres to the papiſts, that plead for their hierarchie, with the ſame reaſons that M. D. doth for his, doe determine, that the government our Bbs. exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe ouer other Miniſters, is <hi>iure humano,</hi> by the poſitiue lawe of man onely: the which, if M. D. ſaith true, is falſe: and ſoe the Papiſts are lefte
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15958:3"/>vnanſwered: yea a doctrine contrariant to the lawes of our land,
<note n="(e)" place="margin">S Edw. Cooke de ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re Regis ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtico. fol. 8.</note> which make it one parte of the Kinges juriſdiction, to graunt to our Bbs. that eccleſiaſticall povver they novv exerciſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer us: &amp; alſo to tak it from them at his pleaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re: the which his Highnes taketh to himſelf, &amp; giueth to all Kinges, where he profeſſeth,
<note n="(f)" place="margin">in his premonitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before one of his laſt bookes.</note> that God hath lefte it to the libertie, &amp; freewill of princes, to alter the Church-gouerment at their pleaſure. Laſtly, it is a doctrine contrary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the doctrine of the Church of England, profeſſed even by the Bbs. themſelues
<note n="(g)" place="margin">Bb, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well in his Apolog. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. Arch. Bb. white<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gifte ag: M. Cart.</note> till of late daies: when as men wearie to holde any longer <hi>in Capite</hi> &amp; of the Kinge: they began to change their tenure into <hi>ſoccage,</hi> and deſyred to be free even from <hi>Knights ſervice.</hi> The newnes and ſtrangnes of which doctrine notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge, (to uſe the words of Socrates
<note n="(h)" place="margin">Plato in Apolog. Socratis.</note> againſt his accuſers) M. D. hath told his tale ſoe hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomely, &amp; carried the matter ſo ſmothely, like<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly &amp; confidently; that every word he ſpeaketh, hath an appearance &amp; promis of truth, though
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15958:4"/>in truth, he hath ſcarce uttered one word of truth. By reaſon whereof, I ſawe much hurt was lik to come to the Church of God. The pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts would be much advantaged, ſeing that Antichriſtian doctrine (even after the renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and revivinge of their ceremonies amongſt us) ſoe freely preached and publiſhed, tending to the upholding of their hyerarchie, from the Pope to the Apparitor, aſwell as ours: his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons being in deed the verie ſame with theirs, as in the anſwere to them, it ſhall appeare. Others would be much ſcandalized; thoſe that were in love with their owne eaſe, would eaſily crouch downe lik Iſachars Aſſe, and ſeeing that reſte is good, would readily &amp; without exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, imbrace his doctrine ſoe pleaſing to the fleſhe: as for others, it would <hi>remoras obijcere ardentioribus,</hi> caſt blocks in their waie whoſe hearts were upright with God, and ran well, &amp; ſoe mak themſt and at the gaze like the Corpſes of Aſael &amp; Amaſa: or <hi>retardare zelum,</hi> make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſlack their pace: at leſte <hi>ſanctorum ſpiritus in quie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:15958:4"/>diſquiet the mindes of al the ſaincts, to ſee a ſermon of that conſequence, preached and publiſhed, by a man of that nam &amp; note in the Church. Theſe things conſidered, my hearts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre and praier to God was, that he would raiſe up ſome man, like Moſes to ſtand in the gapp, &amp; by ſome ſhort &amp; ſound anſwere, to make up the breach he had made, and waytinge for the performance of it, the newes was: that work was vndertaken and in hand; but anſwere, and preſſe, &amp; printer, and concealer of the author, were taken and impriſſonned, as dealers againſt the ſtate. Thus was my ſoule caſte downe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in me, to ſee a truth, ſoe profitable &amp; neceſſarie a truth ſuppreſſed. I thought with my ſelf, but ſhall the cauſe lie there? hath no man that cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage for the truth, as to ſett upon that worke a freſhe? I ſawe by experience, that nothing but bands &amp; afflictions abode, him eſpecially, who after this forewarninge ſhould tak up the gant lett M. D. had throwne downe: but knowing of none that was reſolued of it: I caſt my counts
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15958:5"/>and ſummed up my reckonings, &amp; found that my life was not deare to me in this caſe: &amp; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing diſmaied, I ſett downe my reſt, not to be bound onely, but to die alſo for the name of the Lord, &amp; the giving teſtimoney to this parte of the word of his grace. With this reſolution I ſett upon this anſwere, &amp; through the bleſſing of God (who will mainteine his ovvne cauſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all oppoſition of man vvhatſoeuer) have here brought it to thy vievve: in much weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; with many wants I confeſſe: (my ſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the leaſte able of thouſands in this land to manage this buſynes) yet with evidence ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, to make it manifeſt, I doubt not, that M. D. doctrine in this ſermon is nothing leſſe, then <hi>true, profitable &amp; neceſſarie,</hi> as he affirmeth. That his praeface is full of witty caluminations to make our cauſe odious, &amp; our ſelues hatefull to the wourld: &amp; that (notwithſtandinge his great boa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtinge) his ſermon hath in it no one ſound ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable of argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to prove his cauſe &amp; diſprove ours. I have made no large diſcourſes to teach
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15958:5"/>over a nevve the diſcipline of Chriſt: beſides that it belongeth not to me to doe it at this tyme, profeſſing to anſvvere ſo farre onely as he oppoſeth: it hath bin already layd dovvne ſufficiently &amp; at large vvith proofes pregnant and demonſtratiue thoſe fevve of them vvhich M. D. in his ſermon indeavoureth to infringe, I have defended &amp; upheild in this anſvvere o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nely, except that ſometimes I giue him and the reader to vvitt, &amp; as it vvere a taſte, vvhat might further be ſayd therein. According to his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre &amp; my abintie I have diſtinctly applyed my anſvveres to his arguments in order. Weigh them both vvell, good reader, compare the one vvith the other, beleve nether, further then evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence trulie produced, leadeth the: euery ſuch Pythagoras as vvould be beleved upon his ovvne vvord vvithout authoritie &amp; good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, vvas longe ſince condemned
<note n="(i)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ierom epiſt.</hi> 152.</note> 
               <hi>famae nemo credit niſiinconſideratus, quia ſapiens non credit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certo,</hi>
               <note n="(k)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tull in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polog.</hi> c. 7.</note> he is not vviſe but inconſiderate that beleeveth flying and vncerteine ſpeaches, look
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15958:6"/>well therefore to thy evidence, before thou giue thy verdict. Yf thou fyndeſt no ſufficiency in his reaſons to inforce thee to acknowledg his doctrine for true, juſtly think with thy ſelf, it is not elſe where to be had, all men know him to be a ſcholler; he profeſſeth he hath read the cheef treatiſſes on bothſydes, thou haſt here the pith &amp; ſubſtance of all that all of them can ſaie for themſelues and againſt us. The Lord open our eyes to ſee his truth &amp; ſanctifye our hearts vnto the love of it. And the ſame God, the Lord himſelf of peace, graunt us his peace, alwaiſe, by all meanes. To him be praiſe for ever Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:15958:6"/>
            <head>The anſwere to his preface.</head>
            <p>AS the dead flie,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10.1.</note> by falling into the oyntment of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticarie, taketh awaie the ſweete ſmell thereof, &amp; cauſeth it to putrify &amp; ſtink: ſoe doth a man, gratious and glorious for manie good parts, by ſome his follies; looſe the ſweet ſavour of that pretious ointement of his good name, and maketh himſelf to ſtink in their noſtrels, who have moſt delighted in him. What ſhall we ſaie then to M. Downame, &amp; what ſmell is he lik to giue, who in this his preface, hath as many dead flies almoſt as ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. It is directed <hi>to the Chriſtian reader,</hi> the matter concerneth Chriſtianitie, the author a much reſpected Chriſtian; &amp; yet ſcarce one ſentence theirof, but ſoe vnchriſtianly written, that had not G. D. ſubſcribed it, we could never have deemed M. D. the Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of it. It was expected of all that know him, that though he writ of the ſame ſubject, which other his predeceſſours have done; yet, as lead by another ſpirit, he would have take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> another courſe; &amp; by his myld &amp; moderate dealing, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned them for ſharpening their toungs, to make their words cutt as the raſor, &amp; pearſe vnto the heart lik the prickings of the ſword: but he ſurpaſſeth, at leſte doth paralell, &amp; ſoe doth juſtifie the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all. In deed, he covereth with another coveringe, &amp; maketh another ſhewe, then they have done: but when his plaites ſhalbe vnfolded and he vncovered, I doubt not (Chriſtian reader) but thou wilt readily &amp; <hi>ex animo</hi> ſubſcribe my ſentence. Lett us therefore come to it. All that he ſaith in this his preface maie well be referred to four heades. The firſt is his perſwaſion grounded upon reaſon, that whoſoever read his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon without prejudice, cannot but beleeve and imbrace the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine therein taught, as <hi>a truth profitable and neceſſarie</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teyned fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the begininge to the middeſt of page 4. The ſecond, is <hi>a deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of the ſinguler god, that will immediately followe upon the belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinge and imbracing thereof,</hi> from thence to middeſt of page 8. The third is a <hi>double exhortation drawne from the premiſſes,</hi> from thence
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15958:7"/>to the laſt ſentence. The fourth is, his concluſion with a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation.</p>
            <p>His perſwaſion he laieth downe in the beginninge where he telleth us, that he is <hi>not ignorant how vnpleaſing his ſermon will be to ſome, who are foreſtalled with preiudicate opinions, (whom he could wish he were as ſure to perſwade, as he hopeth by evidence of truth to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince;) and that if he maie intreate us, to read it without preiudice, and to iudge of it without partiallitie, he doubteth not,</hi> but that <hi>we will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge with him, that the doctrine therein conteyned is not onely true, but alſo a profit able and neceſſarie truth.</hi> The which in effect he repeateth againe in the latter end of this firſt head. For anſwere wherevnto, (not to examine him what might be the reaſon of this complaint, whether the corrupt meaſuring of other mens mindes by his owne affections, as they now ſtande towards them &amp; their writings that differ from him; or the remembrance of his former paſſions, what time he himſelf was diſpleaſed with them that ſpake againſt him, when he walked in another maie then now he doth; or his feare (being privie to the weaknes of his cauſe) that ſome will too narrowly ſifte and trie his ſermon, if they be not frighted from it by ſome ſuch prefaces; not to examin him I ſaie herof but leaving it to himſelf, not to his pen but to his conſcience to decid) I muſte tell him; firſt that if the prejudice he chargeth upon others, had not blinded his owne eyes, he might well have ſeene, how much he miſtaketh the matter, when he ſaith, he is <hi>not ignorant how vnpleaſing his ſermon willbe to ſome &amp;c.</hi> He cannot be ignorant, that if he hath done the deed he boaſteth of, &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that which he intended therein, none in this kingdome will more applaud this ſermon, &amp; gratulate him with his labours, then thoſe ſome, whom, he ſaith, it wilbe moſte vnpleaſing vnto: con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſidering how deare a price they have payd, and ſtand yet indebted to paie for not being of his mind. A farr greater (I ſuppoſe) then
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15958:7"/>can be imagined he or any of his ſyd will ever diſburſe for it. Purt caſe, the caſe ſhould alter, ſhall we think he or they will abid ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſion, deprivation, degradation, excomunication &amp; impriſſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for this doctrine conteined in his ſermon; as ſome of us have done for the truth we holde? Secondly, that he dealeth not verie charitablie, in chargeing all thoſe that are not of his mind, <hi>to be ſoe foreſtalled with preiudicate opinions, that though, by evidence of truth they be convinced, yet they will not be perſwaded.</hi> What is this els, but to proclaime them to be men,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.21.</note> without conſcience and care <hi>to try all things and keep that which is good?</hi> yea to be ſuch, as againſt light &amp; cheke of heart, are reſolued to goe on in evill, even ſould to the defence of error &amp; obſtinacie? we are often thus charged in this preface, but if he be not able to inſtance, upon his owne know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge in ſome of us, thaz we have ſhewed our ſelues obſtinate in ſome errors, wherof we have bin convicted; himſelf is the man that is foreſtalled with prejudice: and in deed ſoe ſick of this diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, that it maie well be ſayd to him, <hi>medite cura teipſum, hypocrite, first caſte the beame out of thyne owne eye.</hi> For were he as ſound ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of as he would ſeeme to be, he could never have charged (as he doth in the next words) all thoſe that read his ſermon, &amp; doe not aſſent thereto without contradiction, ſtraitewaies acknowledging the doctrine therein conteined to be true, yea a profitable and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie truth: <hi>to read it with preiudice, &amp; iudge of it with partiallity.</hi> A verie hard condition layd upon the reader, and an vncharitable taxe of thowſands in this lande. Thirdly, he boaſteth as vainely of himſelf, as he ſpeaketh vncharitablie of others, for wherevnto tend his words but to tell us, that he is the man, that hath dryven the naile to the head &amp; ſtroke all dead; ſo farre excelling all that writte or ſpak before him, in bringing light out of darknes, that all thoſe who wilfully ſhutt not their cies, muſt needs, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge with him that for true which is in deed utterly falſe. Shall
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15958:8"/>we think M. D. writeth as he thinketh? And that if the Diſcipline we ſtand for, were not (but the government by our Bbs. in ſtead therof) under the croſſe, and he ſhould be (as others are) deprived of all he hath for holding the ſame: ſhall we thinke he would then make ſuch a ſermon, and print it with ſuch boaſting, that all muſt needs acknowledg it for truth, yea for a profitable and neceſſarie truth; or elſe they read it with prejudice, and judge of it with par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tialitie? M. D. muſt give us leave to doubt of it; he cannot be igno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rant that there are manie amongſt us, who ſavour the Bbs. calings ſoe farre as to allow them a place in the Church, and therefore ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be charged with the prejudice and partiallity he ſpeaketh of, who yet nether doe (nor are likely ever to) acknowledg this his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine to be as he ſaith, a profitable and neceſſarie truth. His rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon therefore, wheron he groundeth his perſuaſion, had need to be pregnant, or elſe it is but a vaine preſumption. Let us heare it, <hi>I the rather conceyve this hope</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>becauſe the time hath bin, when myne affection inclined by the reverent opinion I had worthily conceyved not onely of M. Calvin, the author, but alſo of M. Beza, and manie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther godly and learned men, patrones and fautors of the pretended diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, made me ſuſpend my iudgment, till I had ſeriouſly entred into the studie thereof. The which for a longe tyme I did forbeare &amp;c.</hi> Loe here his reaſon; would one think that ſoe skillfull a workman could buylde ſoe ſtronge hope (as not to doubt of it) upon ſo weake a ground; that becauſe himſelf (prejudiced by the reverent opinion he had of thoſe worthy men) <hi>once doubted till he had ſeriouſly entred into the ſtudy thereof;</hi> therefore all others that <hi>reade his ſermo without preiudice,</hi> will forthwith and vvithout doubt <hi>acknovvledge the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine therein conteined to be true, yea a profitable and neceſſarie truth?</hi> Can a man lovve in his ovvne eies, ſo highely eſteeme of his ovvn learning, as to think more to preveile by one little ſermon; then
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15958:8"/>all his Predeceſſours of all degrees, Arch. Bbs. Bbs. Deanes and Doctors, by their large, moſte accurate and learned treatiſſes, have bin able to doe? to buyld ſuch caſtles in the ayer, had more become ſuch a light head as M. G. P. then ſo grave advivine as M. G. D. hath ſemed to be. And did the reuerent opinion of thoſe godly &amp; learned men, make him to ſuſpend his judgment herein? ſoe he ſaith; ſoe alſo did the creditt of the firſt devyſers ſomewhat amaze Bb. Bilſon himſelf as he telleth us;
<note n="(b)" place="margin">in his pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>face to his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet: gou:</note> maie we beleve them? did the reuerence and credit of thoſe worthies, ſoe farr preveile with ſuch great men as theſe, as to amaze the one, and occaſion the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, of longe tyme to ſuſpend his judgment? what merveile then, if the authoritie, of the ſame men, &amp; all ſoundly reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in the world, doe incline us, (whom M. D. thinketh many waies inferior to himſelf) to be of their judgment, or as leſtewyſe to ſuſpende it, till we can ſee more pregnant proofes then have yet bin produced to the contrarie? And ſurely, did the Bbs. in their proceedings, or M. D. in his writings, uſe that moderation which their places and profeſſion require; they ſhould deale much more favourablie with us, then they doe: ſeing if we erre, are we alone? have we not thoſe godly and learned men of our ſyd, by the reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of whom our Adverſaries themſelves have ſtood at a ſtaie for a time? And if M. D. proofes be not (as he affirmeth) pregnant and plentifull in deed; ſhall we not doe well, to be wel advyſed, before we forſake that cauſe, which hath ſoe manie godly and lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned patrones &amp; fautors, as <hi>are ſound, admirably ſound, and orthodoxall in the ſubstanciall points of religion</hi> as himſelf afterwards confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth? verily we cannot be ſoe partiall as to reuerence and admire them in all other pointes of doctrine: and yet deſpiſe them in this of the diſcipline as M. D. and the men of his ſyd doe.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:15958:9"/>
            <p>But in this ſentence of his, I charge him with ſlauder on the one ſyd, &amp; ſuſpect him of vntruth on the other. He maketh M. Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin the author of the diſcipline, (as <hi>Saravia, Bb. Bilſon, D. Kinge</hi> &amp; others have done before him) how ſlandereth he the cauſe of God, ſoe making it the divice of man? that Calvin ſhould deviſe it &amp; thruſt it upon the Church for Gods ordinance; what a notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous evil chargeth he vpon that man, whom he would ſeeme to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence? Oh that M. D. him ſelf were not guiltie of that ſin in this ſermon teaching the gouernment by our L. Bbs. to be Gods or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, which is in deed of mans devyſinge. M. Calvin was ſoe farr from being the devyſer of the diſcipline we ſtand for, that he vvas not ſo much as the firſt preacher and publiſher of it, no not in theſe later ages. <hi>Wicliff, Hus, Luther, Zuinglius,</hi> &amp; others before him, brought the ſame to light, though not ſoe clearely and fully in all the partes thereof, as ſhall in the anſvvere appeare. That he ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended his judgment for along time, maie juſtly be ſuſpected of vntruth. They that have knovvne him in times paſt, (from the time of his entrance into the Miniſtry till he became Doctor eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially) conceyved othervviſe of him, then of one that ſuſpended his judgment in his cauſe; and that not vvithout cauſe, if his vvri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings and note bookes vvere ſeene, &amp; he vvould but tell us, vvhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he never ſupplicated to any for the furtherane therof. But be it true that he did as he ſaith, maie vve not juſtlie charge upon him the neglect of his dutie; in that he entred into the Miniſterie, and took one lyving after another and that with ſubſcription (for ought is knovvne to the contrarie) and yet held the matter in ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence a longe tyme, &amp; reſolued not to be (as he afrervvard ſaith) a meddler on either ſyd? But to proced; he giueth us tvvo reaſons (ſuch as they be) for his excuſe; The firſt is, <hi>he rightly ſuppoſed</hi> (as he ſaith) <hi>his paines might be better beſtowed in other parts of divinitie.</hi> And vvhy ſoe? doth he not affirm this parte to be a <hi>profitable and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15958:9"/>neceſſarie truth?</hi> And hath not God commanded to his Miniſters eſpecially the ſtudie, as of everie parte of his will: ſoe of this ſoe profitable &amp; neceſſarie a truth, as concerneth the government of his Church, the Miniſters and Officers therof? Yea can the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters more profitably beſtowe their paines &amp; ſtudie, then in theſe pointes of divinitie, that are moſte doubted of, &amp; controverted in the Church, vvherof they are members? Yea, are they not bound to it, when the cauſe ſoe ſtandeth that they muſt ſubſcribe to the one, and that the moſte ſuſpected ſide, even ſuch as the moſte and beſte learned in the vvorld approve not? Whether this ſuppoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his be right (as he ſaith) or no, lett the vvorld judge. But to give it the more credit, he telleth us, <hi>how he heard M. Greenham a zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Preacher reprove yonge divines in a ſermon at Cambridge &amp;c, for ſetting up the roofe, before they had layd the foundation.</hi> Al as poore man, vvhat ſuccour is there under this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s shadovv? Yf M. Green<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham ſoe cenſured all yonge divines for ſtudying the Diſcipline, vvhereto can it be imputed, but to ſome diſtempered paſſion, or zeale vvithout judgment in him? not to anie ſound reaſon ſurely, yf vve conſider the matter vvell. Was there not greater reaſon for him, to reprove the Prelates, for urginge yonge divines to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe, to the Diſcipline in controverſy, and ſeeking reſolution in it? Have not yonge divines juſte cauſe to ſtudie it, vvhen ſeing it controverted amongſt manie &amp; great divines old and nevve, they muſt notvvithſtanding beforced to ſubſcribe, and thereby to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove that parte, vvhich they know to be contrarie to the judgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the greateſt lights, that theſe later ages have affoarded the Chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ches of God? Is it not ſtrange, they can be contented men ſhould, (naie will they not condemne them if they doe not) ſubſcribe to that as true; and yet blame them, yf they ſtudie the ſame and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min whether it be true or no? what is it elſe, but vvith the blinde Papiſts, to make ignorance the Mother of Devotion, even to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15958:10"/>as the Church beleeveth, and good enough? yea what elſe is it, but to controule the courſes of our owne, and all vniuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in the world, who require of yonge divines, the publique de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of controverſies of religion, in open ſchooles, &amp; aſſemblies of learned men, and yet denie them the ſtudie, of theſe controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies that trouble our owne Church, though they be deemed not to befoe deep and profound, as other controuerſies are; but ſuch <hi>as eaſynes it ſelf</hi> (if we maie beleeve M. Hooker) <hi>hath onely made harde?</hi> But the truth is, that yonge divines indure no ſuch cenſure, in caſe they ſo ſtudie theſe matters of diſcipline, that they can learne to preach and diſpute and raile againſt them in pulpitts and ſchooles: naie, they are the onely men, that are judged to laie the beſt foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, &amp; pave the readieſt waie for their owne preferment. They onely which ſoe ſtudie the ſame, that they cannot but like and approue the truth of them; they, they, I ſaie, are the vuhappie me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that are ouerbuſye in matters of diſcipline, &amp; ſett up the roofe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they have layd the foundation. In his ſecond reaſon he telleth us, <hi>he could not ſee what good would come either to himſelf or to the Church of God, by his paines taken in that controuerſy, For he conceyved the iſſue of his ſtudie would be, either the diſgrace of his Miniſterie amonge the forwarder ſort, if he reſolued as no whe hath done: or the ouerthrowe of his Ministerie, if he should ſtand for that diſcipline.</hi> Wherein, beſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des his vncharitablenes renued, mark how he diſcouereth one ſhame whileſt he aſſaieth to cover another. What elſe can it argue, but that he walked not in the execution of his function with ſoe right a foote and ſyncere affection as he ought to have done; had he made ſtreight ſtepps to his pathes, he would have reſpected, not ſo much the grace of men, how holie and forward in ſhew ſoeuer; as the diſcharge of that office, which God impoſed on him, &amp; is to be parformed without reſpect of parſons. And is it any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther but a vaine and ambitious minde, ſoe to feare the diſpleaſing of ſome, and the diſgrace of his Miniſtry with them, as in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15958:10"/>to forbeare of alonge tyme, the ſcarching out of that divine truth, which himſelf affirmeth to be both profitable &amp; neceſſarie? Of as ill note is it, that he refuſed ſoe to doe, for ſeare leſte in ſeing the truth &amp; profeſſing it, <hi>it would be the ouerthrowe of his Miniſtert:</hi> can this be any better then Symonie and intruſion? had not G. D. ſubſcribed this ſentence, I could not have thought he had looked ſoe farre a ſquinte, &amp; ſought himſelf ſo much. But obſerue we ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, hovv he vvrongeth thoſe vvhom he calleth in a kind of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deine, <hi>the forwarder ſort</hi> as though the Miniſterie of thoſe onely that diſlik the preſent government, vvere in grace vvith them: &amp; the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie of all others vvere contemned &amp; diſpiſed of them; ſoe his vvords importe, though vncharitablie. For hovvever, the forvvar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſort, (that is, ſuch as goe before others in vvelldoing) vvould lik the better of thoſe Miniſters that approue of the preſent gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yf they vvere of judgment for the diſcipline of Chriſt: yet ſo longe as they ſhevve themſelves faithfull &amp; painefull in all other duties of their Miniſterie, and doe not ſin of mallice in rayling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it; all the vvorld ſeeth, hovv they yeild due reverence vnto them, &amp; their Miniſterie. M. D. having thus layd dovvne the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of his ſuſpence, ſhevveth us the grounde of his reſolution to ſtu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>die it, vvhere he ſaith, <hi>that when of late yeares the cauſe was ſoe alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the time, that a neceſsitie was impoſed on him to reſolue &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe on the one parte: he entred on the studie therof parhaps with another mind then ſome others did, &amp; therefore with other ſucceſſe.</hi> Wherof I can make no other conſtruction but this, an I leave his conſcience to be examined by the ſearcher of hearts, vvhether it be not the meaninge of theſe cloudy ſpeaches, that vvhen of late his conceited deſyres &amp; other hopes of reformation in the begininge of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſties reigne did fayle him, &amp; that he parceyved the caſe to be ſo al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tered, that except men vvould approue the gouerment eſtabliſhed, &amp; the Corruptions theirin, by ſubſcribing &amp; conforming to them; they muſt be turned out of their livings: he then began to think himſelf of the beſte &amp; clenlieſt vvaie to tak his leave of that cauſe, and to be enterteined of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15958:11"/>the contrarie. What that <hi>other minde</hi> ſhould be, which brought <hi>other ſucceſse,</hi> I know not. Yf he meaneth that diſcontented needy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſett him a work, and plunged him with a deſyre of yelding, no merveil though God anſwered him after the immagination of his heart, and gaue him leave to goe, that would needs be gone: but lett that other mind be farre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> us to ſtudie with. Yf he mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, that ſingle and ſincere affection which ſetting a parte all wourldlie reſpects, vnfeynedly deſyreth to be informed in the truth; ſee we not how vncharitablie he chargeth all his brethren that have in their ſtudies reſolued againſt the hierarchie, that they ſtudied not the cauſe, with that ſingle and ſyncere heart that he did? But lett us heare him ſpeak againe, and tell us what mind it was; to witt, that he conſidered with himſelf, firſt <hi>that it was ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall and damnable preſumption to make ſeparation from our Church which holdeth and profeſſeth all ſubſtanciall pointes of divinitie as found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as any Church in the world, the primitiue Churches not excepted &amp;c. and wherein the meanes of ſalvation are ordinarily and plentifully to be had.</hi> Secondly, <hi>that he being in the Miniſterie, neceſsitie was laid up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, and woe vnto him if preached not the goſpell.</hi> And therefore ſtudied theſe <hi>controverſies, as one who ment if he were not convicted with evidence of truth to be reſpondent or defendant, reſolving not to leave his place, vnleſse by force of argument he were remoued wheras o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers being out of loue with our Church diſcipline, &amp; in affection wholly alienated from our Church-gouerners, ſtudied theſe things as opponents and plaintiffs.</hi> Wherein firſt, he ſpeaketh ydlely, ſeing it is not mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall touching the truth, whether he cam as a reſpondent or oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent to the ſtudie of theſe controverſies. Everie reſpondent doth not defend the truth, nether doth euery opponent oppugne it: ſome that defend, daube with vntempered morter, plead for Baal, and buyld up Babel. others that oppone, doe vvorthily in caſtinge dovvne by the vvord of God, their vvalles and Caſtles. Secondly,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15958:11"/>ſeing that <hi>other minde where with he ſtudied, was not to leave his stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding &amp;c.</hi> What do the he againe, but charge others to be ſuch fooles and ſottes, as to forſake their ſtandings, though by force of argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they be not convinced; But what ſtanding doth he meane? was it the paſtorall charge of that flock, that now dependeth on him? it ſeemeth no; for he that lefte <hi>Lotheburie</hi> for it; and would have lefte it for <hi>Wiggen,</hi> in all likelihood will leave it for greater preferment. What then, is it the office of the Miniſtrie? verely whatſoever he ſaith concerninge his purpoſe, this his ſermon ſheweth, he ſtudied theſe controuerſies as one, who neuer mente to looſe his ſtanding for the truth of the diſcipline, ſoe longe as by any colour, he could clude the arguments brought for it. As for his firſt reaſon, <hi>that he held it ſchiſmaticall and damnable preſumption to ſeparate from our Church &amp;c.</hi> Not to inſiſt upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his high &amp; peremp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>torie compariſon, which will hardlie be made good by him, yf we conſider who they are that arrogate the title of the Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>land; the vncerteinty of the doctrine they holde, altering and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryinge as it is expound dand interpreted at their pleaſure, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially that ſitt in the ſea of Canterburie, and the impugninge of diuerſe parts of the truth by preaching and printinge, the cheefe prelates winckinge, yf not approving, and in a ſorte provyding it maie be done impune. Nor yet to ſtand upon it, that however in manie places, the word is ſoundly and plentifully preached; yet partly through the greate ecclipſe lately made, by the ſilencing of ſoe many preachers, and putting out ſoe worthy lightes, which lieth heavy upon many a ſoul; &amp; partly through the dailie letting and holding in, of many dombe idols and blinde guides, togither with the pride, ambition, covetouſnes, &amp; voluptuouſnes of others; yf M. D. look about the feilds well, he ſhall find the harveſt great and the labourers few, no ſpringes of living water in manie places to refreſh thirſtie ſoules: many little ones asking bread, but have no
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15958:12"/>Fathers to giue it the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; others in ſtead their of, giving ſtones, ſerpent, ſcorpions to eate of, &amp; ſtinking puddles to drinke on: in vvhich reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects there cannot but be great cauſe of ſorrovv &amp; grife to a godly heart; Not to ſtand upon theſe things I ſaie, but granting it, to be even as he vvould have it (the times of the primitiue Church ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted) vvhat vvill follovv thereon, either for his ovvne defence or our hurt? nothing I trovv: vnleſſe he be of mind &amp; can main<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teine it, that it is ſchiſmaticall &amp; damnable preſumption for a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, in his judgment to differ from thoſe Churches vvhereof he is a member, in any point: or that to refuſe ſubſcription &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie to them in everie thinge, (provided <hi>they holde &amp; profeſſe all ſubſtanciall pointes of divinitie</hi>) be, to make ſeparation from it. M. D. I doubt not, is parſvvaded the Churches of Scotland, France and the lovve cuntries holde and profeſſe all ſubſtanciall pointes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: &amp; that in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the meanes of ſalvation is ordinarily &amp; plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully to be had; vvhat if he vvere a member of any one of thoſe Churches, &amp; required by them to ſubſcribe for truth, that the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerment of the Church, <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>muni praesbyteroru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conſilio,</hi> by the preſby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie is jure divino: &amp; the gouerment by our L. Bbs. is not divine, but humane &amp; <hi>iure poſitiuo,</hi> maie it be thought, he vvould count it ſchiſmaticall &amp; damnable preſumption, to be of another minde? And if for refuſing to ſubſcribe in that manner, (vvhich if his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be true vvere a greate fault) he ſhould be putt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his Miniſterie, &amp; out of the Church: might it be ſayd, he made ſeparatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from it? verely, yf a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt goe againſt his ovvne judgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; mind there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; becauſe the Church vvherof he is a member, profeſſeth all the ſubſtanciall pointes of divinitie; &amp; having in it the meanes of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, holdeth ſoe; vvhat doe vve elſe, but make, the Church, or rather the gouernors thereof, Popes &amp; Gods, yea lifte the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> up aboue all that is called God? But further, yf it be ſchiſmaticall &amp; damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble preſumption, to ſuffer our ſelves to be cutt of fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the execution of our Miniſterie, in the Church vvherof vve are members, rather then againſt Conſience to yeld to euery thinge it requireth of us; vvhat is it in our Prelates, by ſuſpencion, deprivation &amp; degradatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:15958:12"/>to cutt of fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Miniſterie, ſuch as hold &amp; profeſſe all the ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciall pointes of divinitie as ſoundly, &amp; practyce them as carefully, as the beſte of them all (none diſpraiſed) becauſe they cannot, nor vvill not force their conſciences, to yeild to ſome other ſmaller matters as themſelues count them? yea by excomunication, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as heathens &amp; publicanes, to cutt them of fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Church? is this no preſumption in them? vvell, vvhether they or vve be guilty of ſchiſme lett Councels &amp; Fathers judge. <hi>Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticus eſt, qui a comunione ſeipſum ſuſpendit &amp;c. he is a ſchiſmatik,</hi> ſaith the councell of Calcedon
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret. pr.</hi> 2 <hi>Cauſ.</hi> 23. <hi>q.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 42.</note> 
               <hi>which ſeparateth himſelf from the comu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nion &amp;c. Schiſma ab eccleſia ſeparat, ſchiſme ſeparateth from the Church,</hi> ſaith Ierom. <hi>Schiſmatici ſunt ijſdem vtentes ſacramentis, at diſſentientes opinionibus ſeorſum celebrant conventus. They are ſchiſmatikes,</hi> ſaith Auſtin,
<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>de ve ra religs oneca.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>who though they uſe the ſame ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes ſtill that the Church doth: yet varying in opinions, doeſeparate from it, &amp; holde meetings a parte by themſelues:</hi> the vvhich I hope M. D. vvill not charge upon us: It vvere vvell. he could cleare our oppoſites aſvvell as vve can our ſelues of this crime, they are the men, if vve maie beleeve Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin, that run vvithin that cenſure. <hi>Quicun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> invident bonis ve que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant occaſiones excludendieos, aut degradandi, vel crimina ſua ſic defen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dere parati ſunt, ſi abiecta velprodita fuerunt, ut etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conventiculoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregationes vel eccleſiae perturbationes cogitant excitare, iam ſchiſmatici ſunt &amp;c.</hi> Whoſoeuer (ſaith he)
<note n="(f)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hipe rius de ſacr: ſtud: non deſcrend. p.</hi> 76.</note> 
               <hi>envye thoſe that are good, &amp; ſeek oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to exclud &amp; degrad the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; are ſoe ready to defend their faultes, that rather then they will leave the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they will devyſe how to raiſe up troubles in the Church, &amp; dryve men from it into cunventicles and corners, they are the ſchiſmatikes, though they be not divided from the Church &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In his ſecond reaſon he telleth us, hovv he <hi>conſidered that being in the ministerie, neceſsitie was laid upon him, and a woe if he preached not the goſpell.</hi> Which conſideration I vviſhe more familiar to him, &amp; others that ſeeme litle to regard it: but doth he think it proper to him? knovv he, that others vvho have laboured in the miniſterie as faithfully &amp; painfully as he; &amp; have that teſtimony of loving &amp; ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ving vvith their flocks depending upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (though novv deprived
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ad Titum Ca.</hi> 3.</note>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:15958:13"/>of them) vvhich he hath not; have ſeriouſly conſidered the ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſſity layd upon them, and notvvithſtanding that <hi>woe,</hi> knovv no ſuch neceſſity as to redeeme the libertie of preaching vvith the bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dage of conſcience, and the doing of thoſe things vvhich God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biddeth. But hovv can that neceſſity he upon us? Doth not the Apoſtle there ſpeake, of them onely to vvhom the diſpenſation is committed, but doe it not at all, or not vvillinglie through their ſloth and negligence? We for our parts, deſyre nothing more vvil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, then to have againe that libertie of preaching vvhich once vve had, vvherein vve ſhevved not our ſelves ſoe unvvillinge and negligent as manie of our oppoſites doe; and from vvhich, becauſe ſome of us vvill not be bound, vve are bounde in priſſon, as the <hi>Gatehouſe</hi> at this daie can teſtifie. And (to ask M. D. a queſtion) yf he were injoyned (to ſpeak nothing of ſubſcription which will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be juſtifyed whileſt the world ſtandeth) to weare, with his ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plice and doctorall robes, habit, hood, tippet, preiſts gowne and cloak, the graie Amice, &amp; the reſt of the induments &amp; ornaments of the popiſh preiſthood, to tak upon him a ſhaven crowne that honorable mark of preiſthood, (which his good L. to whom he dedicateth his ſermon, as it is ſayd, would not refuſe (to croſſe often, to duck &amp;c. in the adminiſtration of the ſupper, to kiſſe the pax, to giue holy bread and ſprinckle with holy water, and to ſwallow manie ſuch gnattes, all which are no worſe then the thinges re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of us (as we are ready to mainteine, yf we maie have ſuch an indifferent tryall as the <hi>modeſt offer</hi> mencioneth) yf theſe things I ſaie, were injoyned him, would he think that ſuch a neceſſitie is layd upon him to preach, that he muſt yeld to the doing of them, rather then ſuffer himſelf to be putt from his ſtandinge? Many in deed doe ingenuouſly confeſſe, that in ſuch a cauſe they would ſwallow many ſuch guatts; yea admitt and devoure all popiſh rites and ceremonies how filthy &amp; abhominable ſoever) being waſhed
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15958:13"/>with engliſh water, ſuch <hi>a woe</hi> heth upon them if they preach not the goſpell, though in deed they preach verie ſeldome. Is M. D. of theire mind too? we for our paries have not ſo learned Chriſt, but think rather, that a neceſſitie is laid upon all men in ſuch caſes not to preach; &amp; a <hi>woe</hi> not farr from them that will preach with ſuch conditions, and admitt none therevnto but with ſuch proviſoes, eſpecially when ſuch a neceſſitie is layd upon us. Is not that man blinde of his right eie, think ye, that can ſee a <hi>woe</hi> againſt them, that ſuffer (that which they cannot hinder) themſelues to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of their miniſterie, rather then they will yeld to matters vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lawefull: but no <hi>woe</hi> to them that who depriue us for ſuch matters &amp; forbidd us to preach to the gentiles that they maie be ſaved? To proceed, M. D. having ſhewed with what mind he ſtudied the con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trouerſy, telleth us, in the next words, that others ſtudyed it (being out of loue with our gouerment and gouernours) as opponents &amp; plaintiffs, that is, with purpos to oppoſe, not yeild to the truth, how cleare ſoeuer it ſhould appeare to them: where was his Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Charitie, trow we, when he wrote this? Although we ſee no great cauſe in the gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t by our L. Bbs. why we ſhould be in love with it, conſidering it is neither the beſt nor any plante at all of the Lords ſetting in his vynearde, and therefore in due time to be ſupplanted by him: And albeit we cannot much abound in har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty affection towards the gouernours themſelues who, having got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten an inche of his Magiſtie, doe take an elue, and not onely reigne as Lords ouer their brethren: but againſt all law depriue, degrade, ſuſpend and excomunicate them, many of whom are not much inferior in many graces to the beſt of them; yet have we not bin ſo farr out of loue with the one, nor our affectione ſoe farr eſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from the other, as to ſtudie theſe controuerſies with no other mind but to oppoſe to the truth as M. D. calumniouſly ſuggeſteth; however by the ſtudy of them, we fynd juſte cauſe to be ſoe farre
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15958:14"/>out of loue with them both, as not to ſubſcribe to the lawfullnes of the one, or giue allowance to the oppreſſions of the other. In the next place, M. D. laieth downe the ſucceſſe that followed upon our ſo ſtudying of it, as that <hi>we have ſought knots in rushes ſtreyned at euery gnatt, picked ſoe manie quarrels againſt our Church &amp; miniſterie, that we have ſuffred our ſelues to be depriued, the land to ſwarme (even in our owne opinion) with Papists &amp; Atheiſts, our owne places to be deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, or occupied with ſuch as we account vnprofitable Miniſters, &amp; all this, rather then we will ſo much as without preiudice &amp; partiallity read what is truly ſayd for the defence of our Church.</hi> I hope he hath the grace to bluſhe at leaſt, when he conſidereth what he here chargeth upon us. Is it a ſeeking of knottes in ruſhes, a ſtreining at gnattes &amp; picking of quarrels with our Church; to contend for the truth, &amp; labour to purge out the corruptions of the Church? what ſhall we ſaie then to Elias, who indeavoured the clenſing of Iſrael from the alters of Baal? to the Angel, who troubled the water to cure the ſick? what elſe doe we but ſeek to cure the ſickneſſes &amp; diſeaſes in the Church, yf we trouble it? doe we pick quarrels who deſyre a plaiſture for health? quid agunt qui reſultant, what doe they which keep it from the ſoare? yf vve; becauſe vve vvould preſerue the vvor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhip &amp; ſervice of God vndefyled? vvhat doe they, vvho vvill not abide the purging of it from the vncleane things of Antichriſt? Let Caſſander an Adiaphoriſt be Iudge vvho they be that pick quarrels, he telleth us,
<note n="(g)" place="margin">G. Caſſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſulta: act. 7.</note> that though the proteſtants in their Godly zeal did at the firſt ſharplie reproue certeine manifeſt abuſes; yet the cheefe cauſe of the Churches diſtraction at that tyme, <hi>(illis aſsignan dam eſſe, qui inani quodam faſtu eccleſiaſticae potestatis inflati, recte &amp; modeste admonentes, ſuperbe contempſerunt &amp; repulerunt)</hi> is to be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed to them, vvho puffed up vvith that arrogant pride of the eccleſiaſticall povver, ſcornfully contemned and deſpyſed thoſe that rightfully and modeſtlie admoniſhed them. The vvhich, to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15958:14"/>vvhom it novv apperteineth, vvho ſeeth not? vvho are they that ſtill croſſe us, even ſo much the more that in all humility, we ſue and ſeek for reformation of things amyſſe, as if the Taskmaſters of Egipt vvere making Iſraels burthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, the more heavy, the more they ſought for libertie? <hi>vbi ſpiritus contentionis veraciter pugnat, veritas ipſa indicat,</hi> I vvill accuſe none, lett the truth it ſelf ſhevve, vvho be they that picke quarrels. But to proced; Is it our opinion onely that the land ſvvarmeth vvith Atheiſts &amp; Papiſts? is it not the judg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of all, that have any judgment at all? hath M. D. the face to deny it? That manie of our places are ſupplied by ſuch as are vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable Miniſters, men frutefull in nothing but in the vnfrutefull vvorks of darknes, that preach not at all; or if they doe; their ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues vvere better cleave to the roofs of their mouthes; is too true. And hovvſoeuer M. D. here to ſave his head from breaking ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth the matter, by ſaying <hi>ſuch as we account vnprofitable,</hi> as if it vvere not ſoe in deed; Yet Gods people ſee and feele the contrarie, and M. D. himſelf alſo hath publiſhed it to all the vvorld in his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of the dignitie and duties of the Miniſters. But vvhere and in vvhom is the fault? that is the queſtion in deed: M. D. caſteth it up on us, for vve muſt beare the blame for all: but lett the matter be carefully inquired into, and the lott caſte, that the tranſgreſſor maie be found out; I dout not, but vve ſhall paſſe by, and ſome others be taken. Who are they that dominere at their pleaſure, that ſcourge their brethren (even faithfull &amp; painefull preachets) with ſcorpions, but have not, or at leſt uſe not ſo much as the leſſe rodd againſt Atheiſts &amp; Papiſts ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t aſſes, doumb Miniſters, abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable nonreſide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, ſcandalous &amp; profane lyvers? nay, are there not more ſuch yearely made in Ember vveeks, as if the bottomeleſſ pitt vvere opened to ſend forth Locuſtes? vvhat rodd I ſaie doe our Bbs. beare them vvith? naie doe they not, make &amp; ordeine the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, admitt &amp; receyve the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue &amp; countena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yea ſuccour &amp; defend the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15958:15"/>While co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to lavv &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, vve are thruſt out of our places, in vvhich vve laboured faithfully &amp; painfully for many yeares? depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of our freeholds, denyed the benefitt of lavv, the comon right of all ſubjects, ſhutt out fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the como<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> refuge &amp; ſanctuarie of the op<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>preſſed, denyed the proſecution of our appeales, &amp; offring to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue them, &amp; to preach for the hindring of the increaſe of thoſe ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>min he ſpeak of? are vve not clapt up in priſſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; there kept vvithout bayl or maineprize, till vve take an oath, or giue ſufficient caucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to meddle no more in any miniſteriall action, no nor ſo much as to teach or catechize our ovvn families, any other parſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being preſent? this is our verie cauſe, &amp; this doe the priſſons vvittnes at this daie: hovv then doth M. D. laie all the blame upon us, as the heathen vvere vvont to doe vpon the Chriſtians? and hovv doth the D. plaie the ſophiſter, in ſetting dovvne a falſe cauſe for a true, &amp; making us the cauſe vvhy Atheiſts, and Papiſts increaſe? might he not aſvvell charge us vvith ſuffering the povvder plott and dit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers? But it paſſeth aboue all, that he chargeth us <hi>to doe all this, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then we will ſoe much as read without preiudice &amp; partiallity, what is trulie ſayd for defence of our Church;</hi> then which, what can be ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more vncharitably and vainely; as if all that imbrace not confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, reade allwaiſe with partiallity and prejudice; &amp; as if whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is written by our oppoſites, were ſufficient to ſatisfy everie one, that is not foreſtalled with prejudice, &amp; none had layd it by when he read, but M. D. himſelf. But whether that which he or others have ſayd, be truly ſayd for the defence of the Church, or rather of the corruptions in our Church, &amp; how we have read the ſame, doth in parte appeare by that we have already written, and would doe, yf fredome were permitted to the preſſe, &amp; we might without perill and extreme charge publiſh our anſwers, as others vente &amp; broach their oppoſitions; they maie ſpeak &amp; write what pleaſe them, &amp; call for our anſweres; but we muſt keep ſilence or kiſſe the priſſons &amp; abid the cenſures, while they tryumph &amp; ſaie
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:15958:15"/>we reade with prejudice. Well lett us now goe on with him, having dealt thus Chriſtianly with others he returneth to his tale againe concerninge himſelf, &amp; telleth us what he found when he <hi>had ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died ſom the cheef treatiſſes on both ſydes,</hi> to vvitt, <hi>on the one ſyde, certeine places of ſcripture, drawne as it were by the neck to that ſyde, a fewe ſtrag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gling ſentences quoted out of the Fathers, &amp; as it were with oares wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried by theſe men (looking as one would think the other waie) against the full straeme of antiquities, ſome prettie ſpeaches &amp; wittie proofes, which yet were but meere colours rather then ſound arguments; On the other ſyd, full &amp; plentifull proofes, eſpecially in the treatiſſe of the perpetuall gouerment, from which he receyved good ſatisfaction,</hi> and as he after ſaith, <hi>would ſatisfy others alſo, yf they would ſett preiudice a ſyd,</hi> what a flooriſh is here? as if <hi>Dioſcorus</hi> were aliue againe, lifting up his voice in the Calcedon Councell. <hi>Ego defendo dogmataſancto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum patrum, ego illorum habeo teſtimonia, nec obiter in tranſcurſu, ſed in ipſorum libris poſita: ego cum pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribus eijcior &amp;c. That vvhich I mainteine is the doct<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rine of the holy Fathers, I have there vvittneſſes at larg, not ſtragling here &amp; their &amp; gathred up by chance, but take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of their ovvne bookes, I am caſt out vvith the Fathers &amp;c.</hi> A floriſh in deed; as if all learning ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d &amp; honeſt dealing had bin in himſelf &amp; non in the Councell; vvhen in truth he had nether truth nor antiquity on his ſyde, no more then there is in theſe vaine glorious ſpeaches of M. D. The anſwere follovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhall make it manifeſt, that he himſelf &amp; the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that gaue him ſo good ſatisfaction, (with the reſte of their ſyd) are they who vvreſt ſcriptures even vvorſe then papiſts, alleadg Counterfeits in ſtead of Fathers, vvherrie in others as it vvere vvith oares, againſt the full
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15958:16"/>ſtreame of their ovvne meanings, and that there beſt &amp; ſoundeſt grounds, are carnall policies, fleshly perſvvaſions, bitter reproches, ſharp cenſures, ſuſpencions, excommunications, deprivations &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>priſonments, by all vvhich they diſpute &amp; conclude, almoſt all their matters. The ſcriptures &amp; Fathers vve alleadge, are rightly vnderſtood, accordinge to the Circumſtances of the places them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, &amp; the judgement of the beſt &amp; moſte learned vvriters in the vvourld. For the evincing vvhereof, our oppoſites are driven to ſuch ſhifts as is ſtrange to ſee, even to devyſe diue ſe ſtrange ſenſe of one and the ſame place, ſome extending, ſome reſtreyninge, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one dryving to a diuerſe ſenſe, either manifeſtly abſurd, or ſoe obſcure, as if the true meaninge could not be atteyned to. One in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance vvher of, to paſſe by the reſt, lett the Reader veivve vvell, in their handling of 1 tim. 5.17. &amp; Ambroſe upon 1 tim. 5.1. But to goe on; the cheefbook from vvhich M. D. receyved good ſatiſfaction, vvas as he ſaith, <hi>the learned treatiſſe</hi> &amp;c. to vvitt Bb. Bil ſons: vve vvill beleeve him, for he hath little or nothing in all hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſermon vvhich is not in that treatiſe; but ſeing he that vvill parte vvith his frend, as the vvyſeman ſaith, vvill fynd an occaſion to doe it, &amp; vvhen good cauſes vvant. pretences ſhall ſerue the turne; I vvish him to look to it, that other inducements beſt knovvne to himſelf, vvere not more perſvvaſyve and forcible vvith him, then theſe he here ſett dovvne. And vvhere he preſumeth ſoe farre up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on other mens judgments &amp; affections, that they muſt needs turne round by the ſame ſvvaie or poyze, &amp; ſtande &amp; fall as it vvere by the ſame ſtaffe vvith him, if they ſett prejudice a ſyd; (for he ſaith, <hi>he knoweth nothing to the contrary but the ſame arguments that perſwaded him, will preveile with others</hi>) vvhat doth he elſe but follovve the preſumption of error, vvhoſe propertie is, as Auſtin ſaith,
<note n="(h)" place="margin">de gene: cout: Mauich:</note> 
               <hi>ut quod cui<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> diſplicet id alijsquo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> oportere existimet diſi licere, to think that that which pleaſeth or diſpleaſeth it ſelf, muſt needspleaſe or diſpleaſe others
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15958:16"/>alſo:</hi> but as Tertullian to the Valentinians, ſoe maie I ſaie to M. D. <hi>artificium habent quo prius perſuadent, quam doceant, veritas autem do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendo ſuadet, non ſuadendo docet,</hi> M. D. hath great skill to perſvvad before he teach, but the truth perſvvadeth by teaching, teacheth not by perſvvadinge, the judicious reader I doubt not vvill hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to his reaſons, &amp; lett goe ſuch perſvvaſions. Thus much for his firſt head, lett us novv enter upon his ſecond vvherein he shevv eth us vvhat <hi>exceding good</hi> he hopeth to ſee &amp; that <hi>quickly,</hi> in caſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vvould be perſvvaded vvith him: namely <hi>an ende of this pernitious diviſion againſt us;</hi> &amp; vvhy ſoe? becauſe, <hi>though ſome other particulars be controuerted, yet this of the Church-gouerment is the chiefe, &amp; the reſt, as he hath ſometimes thought, are but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouerſies in prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, to avoyde the envy of this. For he doubteth not, but if men ſyncerely affected were right ly perſwaded of the gouerment, either they would not ſo ſtand upon mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of ceremonie &amp; ſuch like of ſmall importance &amp;c. or if any out of ten dernes of conſcience should make ſcruple, that they would favourably be re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſpected.</hi> Here firſt I charge upon him the vvronging, &amp; that verie vnchriſtianly, of manie godly Miniſters in thus judging of them: can it enter into a Chriſtian heart ſo to think, that they have oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the ceremonies, yea &amp; ſuffred for them, not in ſynceritie as being perſvvaded of their vnlavvefullnes, according to their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, but onely in pretence &amp; hypocriſy, &amp; to avoyd the envy of this of the hierarchy? vvhat is this elſe but to calumniate? can he be ignorant, that as the ceremonies have bin oppugned by the Godly before novv, in our neighbour Churches, vvho could not make this controverſy their pretence: ſoe there be diverſe amonge our ſelues, of judgment for the lavvfullnes of the hierarchy jure poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uo, vvho yet ſuffer &amp; are ready to ſuffer more then hath yet bin in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted on them, rather then they will conforme to the allowance or practy ce of the ceremonies? no, no, it cannot be hidd from him, that diverſe of the Miniſters, at the time of their depriuation, were of this judgment, what ever they now are or will be herafter, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they further co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider the matter.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:15958:17"/>Secondly, lett it be obſerved, hovv he counteth all mattersnovv in queſtion for vvhich ſo manie Miniſters have ſuffered, but <hi>triſtes</hi> &amp; (this of the Church gouerment onely excepted) <hi>matters of ſmall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance,</hi> and as he ſayd before, even <hi>knotts in rushes</hi> and <hi>ſeely gnatts:</hi> as light accounet doe all the reſt of that ſyd make of them, &amp; even ſo did Harding tell Iuell, <hi>the things were ſmall, where with he charged their Church.</hi> Wherefore their plea being the ſame, vvith his: vvell maie that vvorthy ruells anſvvere to Harding then, ſerue M. D. turne novve. <hi>How great or ſmall theſe matters are,</hi> ſaith he,
<note n="(i)" place="margin">de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of artic ag: Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings preface.</note> 
               <hi>it forceth not. In deed they are avouched with verie ſmall proofes: as ſmall as you would have them, it appeareth you keep no ſmall ſeriue about them: no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ought to be counted ſmall, where with ſoe manie of Gods people are deceived and ſcandatized &amp;c. Robberie is no leſse in a ſmall matter then in a great, ſaith Plato. A little leaven ſo wreth the whole lumpe,</hi> ſaith the A poſtle. <hi>Alia ſunt frivola &amp; innoxia, alia frivola &amp; noxia</hi> ſaith Gregorie; <hi>though theſe matters be ſmall, yet the evills that riſe of them,</hi> are not <hi>ſmall;</hi> yf they be ſmall, <hi>there is the leſſe hurt in leaving them, &amp; the more wilfullnes in defending them.</hi> Chriſt ſaith, <hi>qui in modico ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quus, &amp; in maiori iniquus, he that is vnfaithfull in a little, will be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfull in much verely the greateſt parte of the land is wearie of them.</hi> Thus farre that bleſſed Iuell; yf M. D. vvill not heare him, lett him giue eare to Auſtin,
<note n="(k)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tom</hi> 10. <hi>Hom</hi> 42.</note> 
               <hi>de minutis guttis flumina implentur, per augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtasrivulas in ſidat aqua, impleturſentina, mergitur navis, ſmall dropps make great fludes, through ſmall riftes the water ſoaketh in, filleth the deck &amp; drownes the shipp.</hi> Could Hamans money recompence the Kings loſſe of the Ievves? no more can theſe their ceremonies of ſmall importance for vvhich our Bbs. ſtand ſo ſtifflie, euer reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pen ce the Churches loſſe of ſo manie vvorthy preachers as are deprived for them: had it not bin more vviſdome in our reuerend Fathers, to have forborne their brethren in thoſe things, themſelues count trifles? yea to caſte thoſe trifles, (I vvill not ſaye their honours too)
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:15958:17"/>into the ſea? the wiſe and skilfull Pilote, <hi>tempeſtate urgente, quaedam exenerat, ut caetera ſalva permaneant,</hi> when the tempeſt inforceth it, emptieth the ſhipp of ſome thinges to ſave the reſt, yea though the wares be pretious, he ſpareth them not: doe our Bbs. well the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to caſte out the Pilots of the ſhipps themſelues, &amp; all to ſave thoſe romiſhe wares, thoſe baſe and vile trifles;
<note n="(l)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. Ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>melman de tradit. part</hi> 1. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>Col.</hi> 377.</note> 
               <hi>Itance propter conſuetudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> (was it once ſayd to Caſſander) <hi>audes iubere ut pij viriqui alias ſyncere docent, eijciantur?</hi> and maie not the ſame be nowe ſayd in engliſh to our Prelates? Is it even ſoe, are theſe matters of ſmall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, trifeling cuſtomes; hovv dare you then for them, caſt out of the Church, Godly men who otherwiſe teach well and ſynce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely? But to proced, obſerue we ſecondly, how he faileth utterly in the maine drifte and purpos of his ſermon, which is, by bringing men to the imbraceing of his doctrine concerninge the hierarchie, to compound all other the controuerſies amongſt us, ſoe his words ſhewe &amp; both his reaſons, that either the ſincerely affected would not ſtand upon them, or if they did, they ſhould be reſpected: doth he not utterly miſtake the matter? ſeeth he not the cleane contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie before his eies? hovv manic doe approue of the Bbs. calings &amp; yet oppoſe to the ceremonies? vnleſſe therefore he will againe charge them not to be ſyncerely affected; that firſt reaſon of his, is without reaſon. How longe will M. D. giue us cauſe to ſuſpecte he writeth not as he thinketh? we cannot imagin him to be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, how in all ages manie profitable Miniſters howeuer agreeing in matters co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerninge the hierarchy have yet varied about matters of ceremonie: remembreth he not how Auſtin
<note n="(m)" place="margin">
                  <hi>In his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer ad inquiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones I an uarij lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Cap.</hi> 2.</note> in his time com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaineth, <hi>that (tantae fuerunt certationes in eccleſia, de traditioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus humanis, &amp; rebus indifferentibus, ut ſecuta ſit inde miſerabilis vaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas in eccleſia) there were ſoe great contentions in the Church about mens traditions and things indifferent, that the Church was almoste layd waſt therewith?</hi> hath he forgotten that controuerſy about Eaſter,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15958:18"/>
               <note n="(n)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eu ſeb. hiſt. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>Cap.</hi> 23.</note> when, <hi>Neque Anicetus Policarpo perſuadere poterat, neo Policarpus Aniceto ſuaſit,</hi> the contentions of Anicetus &amp; Policarpe, being as Sa lomon ſaith like the barres of a pallace, the one could nor perſwad vvith the other? nay, to come lovver, are the late troubles of our neighbours Churches in Germanie about things indifferent (ſoe called) cleane out of his mind; &amp; hovv many miniſters ſuffred the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. ſelues to be depriued of all for them? yet vvere there no contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſies about the hierarchy. His firſt reaſon then hath nether truth nor likelihood; no more hath his ſecond, yf the experſence of tymes paſt &amp; preſent, can teach us to gueſſe of the times to come? manie are deprived &amp; ſuſpended for the ceremonies notvvithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding they have bin of judgment for the hierarchy, that partely out of their ovvne ſenſe &amp; feeling, &amp; partlie being vvarned by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens harmes, they have learned to make it a parte of their Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanie, to be kept from the Bbs. bleſſing. M. D. vve ſee hath layd a ſlender foundation vvhereon to build his ſucceſſe and great good that vvould come upon the imbraceing of his doctrine, and yet he reareth up many glorious things thereon, &amp; amplifieth the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by a nomber of rhetorications from the conſequentes of yol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in this point, <hi>as compounding of differences, healing of breaches, reuniting of divided mindes, glorifying of God in the edification of his Church, propagation of his goſpell, confuſion of poperi &amp; atheiſme &amp;c. in ſteed of manie evills growing by oppoſing in this point, as dishonor of God and his true religion, advantageing poperie and atheiſm, ſcandalizing whom we ought to edify, both backwarder and for warder ſort.</hi> All vvhich, vvhat are they but vaine ſmoakes eaſely blovvne avvaie; &amp; ſerue for no other uſe in deed, but to make his ovvne vvaie, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e the more handſomely, to have his full ſtrok at them vvhom he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the forvvarder ſort. For vvho knovveth not, that before this vnjuſte Claime of the Bbs. &amp; diuiſion about this point, <hi>that there callings areiure diuino:</hi> &amp; before the tendring &amp; exacting of confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:15958:18"/>&amp; ſubſcription ſoe contrarie to lavv: and before this vvoefull breach made: not by us, but by them that vvill needs ſurgere in al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, dommeire and have their <hi>forth</hi> vijs &amp; modis; vvho knovveth not ſaie, that before this, there vvas no ſuch care and zeale in the Bbs. (manie of them eſpecially) or other their Chapleines for the edification of the Church, propagation of the goſpell, confounding of poperie and atheiſme? doth not their careleſſnes therein, teſtify to their faces? doth not all the vvourld ſee, hovv ſeldome the moſt of them preach, even novv that atheiſm and poperie grovveth ſoe faſt through their ſilencinge of ſoe manie preachers? doe they not for all that, count it the leaſt or no parte of their L. function? doe not their Chancelors, Archdeacons, Deanes, Doctors and Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leins (many of them) heap living upon lyving? defend they not nonreſidencie &amp; other corruptions in the vniuerſities? place they not daily in benefices, idle idols, dumbe dogges that cannot barke? or elſe ſuch doggs or Doegs rather, as loue all vvords that maie doe hurt, ventinge much corrupte popiſh &amp; atheiſticall doctrine, like the doggs in Capitolio, that Tully ſpeaketh of, that barked againſt true men, inſtead of theeves? tollerate they not many in the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie, who notwithſtandinge their gifts, pull downe more by their ſcandalous life, then others can buylde up, like the ſynner Salomon ſpeaketh of, that deſtroieth much good? ſuppreſſe they not faithfull and painefull preachers? yea ſnubb they not &amp; curbe they not (ſo much as lieth in them) euerye one Miniſter or other, of what guifts, pietie and godlines ſoever, in caſe they conforme not to their orders and canons vniuerſally? &amp; in the meane time lett they not Papiſts and Atheiſts goe awaie vnpuniſhed? are not theſe &amp; manie ſuch like the things that diſhonor God &amp; his true re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ligion? hinder the proceeding of the goſpell? advantage popery &amp; atheiſme; ſcandalize ſuch as vve ought to edifye? vvould none of theſe ihings be done any more, yf the poore deprived Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:15958:19"/>would now ſubſcribe that the caling of our Bb. is jure divino? would all this good be done, if this one cotroverſy were at an ende? why then doe our Bbs. themſelues begin and uphold, yea reinfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce the controuerſie? why ſtand they ſo much for their honors, as not to content themſelues to holde their ſoveregneties of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Magiſtrate, as their predeceſſors before them have done, but muſt needs enjoye it now by a new found pattent even jure divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no? at leaſt why leave they not this claime, till ſuch great matters be effected; but preſſe both it, and their beggerly ceremonies more then the lawes of Chriſt, and that to the depriving of ſoe manie worthy preachers, by whoſe miniſtery M. D. himſelf confeſſeth ſo much good might be done? fynaly, why occoſion they ſo manie of all ſorts backward and forward, to be ſcandalized, in ſeeing how they deale for the mſelues ſo zealouſly; for Chriſt ſoe careleſty? But lett us follow him to the ende of this race, where he falleth foule upon the forwarder ſort: (as he calleth them) of whom he maketh two ſorts, to witt, all ſuch Chriſtians in generall as indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to goe before others in weldoinge, and thoſe that published that book, called <hi>the modeſt offer of diſputation &amp;c.</hi> upon both whoſe backes he ploweth and maketh longe furrovves, &amp; leadeth them vvith heavy imputations. The creimes charged upon the former he comprizeth in 5 heads, ſome of them having diuerſe hornes vvherevvith he pusheth hard to gore them; one vvould thinke, althings conſidered, he should have inveighed againſte the former evills, vvith their authors and Fautors; but as if he himſelf vvere one of the <hi>Doegs</hi> before ſpoken of, he ſpendeth himſelf vvhollie upon the true men and letts the robbers goe. His firſt charge is, <hi>that they deſpiſe the ſolemne worship and ſervice of God, and whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever good thinge elſe is ſett forth by authoritie;</hi> A meere calumniation not much differing from Hamans,
<note n="(o)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heſt.</hi> 3.6.8.</note> vvho <hi>thought it too little to laic hands on Mordechaij,</hi> and therefore ſlandered the Ievves, <hi>to be a
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:15958:19"/>people diverſe from others, which kept not the Kings lawes:</hi> except that his mouth runneth more ouer, vvhen he ſaith, <hi>they diſpiſethe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne worship and ſervice of God, and whatſoever good thing elſe &amp;c.</hi> And the ſlander is ſo much the greater, becauſe vve dare boldlie and in the preſence of God affirme, that vve are ſee farre of from the gilte of this crime, that the accuſer of the brethren himſelf, can nor juſtly charge upon us the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tempt of any good thing ſett forth by authoritie, vvhich either vve are perſvvaded is good, or he able to make good. <hi>Obedientiam infringit,</hi> ſaith the old Lindvood rule, <hi>quiſine cauſi id facit,</hi> he is to be charged vvith contempt or diſobedi ence, that can gine no good reaſon of his doinge; the vvorld ſeeth the reaſons of our doings (good as vve are perſvvaded) or elſe lett them be confuted; vvith reuerence &amp; patience vve ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for that vve cannot doe, doth M. D. call that a deſpyſing? is it not rather a fullfilling of the lavv, ſoe farr as it is intended it should be kepte? is it not as ſure a ſigne of ſubjection, &amp; doth it not free as much fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deſpiſing as obebience it ſelf? aske Bb. Bilſon &amp; he vvill tell you:
<note n="(p)" place="margin">Conz. Apol: Seme part 2. pag. 349.</note> vvhy then doth M. D. thus traduce us? It vvere vvell for the Bbs. themſelues and their adherents, (M. D. not excepted). Yf this burſhen laie not heavye upon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then upon us: hovv they regard authoritie, maie eaſily appeare, yf vve conſider there noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious &amp; vvilfull tranſgreſſion of manie good &amp; profitable Canons &amp; conſtitutions; as
<note n="(1)" place="margin">Injunct art. 3.4.</note> that vvhich requireth 12 ſermons yeatly in euery parish
<note n="(2)" place="margin">art 44 &amp; rub: bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm:</note> that vvhich enjoyneth them to catechiſe their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishioners euery fabboth
<note n="(3)" place="margin">Can epiſc pa. 41 16.</note> that vvhich vvilleth them to examine their people before they come to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion
<note n="(4)" place="margin">In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> act art. 23 rub. before the Com.</note> that vvhich de barreth from the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion all notorious offenders
<note n="(5)" place="margin">Injunct art. 20.</note> that vvhich commandeth to keep holy the ſabboth by viſiting the ſick, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciling of enemies betvvene &amp; after the publik exerciſes
<note n="(6)" place="margin">Can: epiſcop. pa. 79.</note> that vvhich requireth private admonition to be uſed before pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique preſentments
<note n="(7)" place="margin">Injunct art. 14.</note> that vvhich allotteth to the poore, the 40
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:15958:20"/>parte of non reſidents livings
<note n="(8)" place="margin">Injunct art. 12.</note> that which appointeth 4. l. yeare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be payd out of euerye livinge worth per annum 100, l. for the keeping of a ſcholler, at the vniuerſitie
<note n="(9)" place="margin">Can: Ep: p 51.</note> that which ſorbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the granting of advouſions
<note n="(10)" place="margin">Can epiſ. p. 25.</note> that which affirmeth plurali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties &amp; non reſidences to be res in ſe ſoeda, in vulgus odioſa, &amp; eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae Dei pernitioſa
<note n="(11)" place="margin">In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junct art. u. 34.34</note> that which injoyneth the aboliſhing out of Churches &amp; houſes all ſuperſtitious pictures &amp; paintings in walles or glaſſewindowes &amp;c. are not theſe Canons &amp; conſtitutions with manie moe, good &amp; profitable &amp; vvell ſett forth by authoritie? are they vvell or ill obſerved by our oppoſites? lett M.D. therefore take back againe this imputation to himſelf &amp; the men of his ſyd, onely I confeſſe, that if <hi>by ſolemne ſervice,</hi> he meaneth that of the organes in Paules &amp; ſuch like places; then in deed vve doe not ſoe highely eſteme therof, as they. His ſecond charge is, <hi>that they not onely vilify and diſgrace the miniſtery of thoſe that are conformable, though not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour, but in many graces by manie degrees ſuperior to manie of thoſe whom they admire; but alſo incourage by all meanes their admired Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters to ſtand out as though they had rather want the food of their ſouls, then not to enioye their fancies &amp;c.</hi> In deed M. D. did vvell to notify vvhat Miniſters he ment; namely not the ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; blinde guides, the ydle and ſcandalous parſons, ſuch as have no conſcience to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute their miniſtrie, though vvith titles and degrees they grovv ſo faſt, that a nevv vvorld muſt be made, or many of them vvill faile of their hopes, and vvant their deſyred dignities: all vvho carrie in themſelues the cauſe of contempt; and are ſoe marked out by M. D. in his former ſermon of the dignitie &amp; dutie of the Miniſters that it is no merveil they be in diſgrace. He meaneth not ſuch I ſaie, but thoſe vvho according to their places and graces take paines a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge their people, though othervviſe conformable. Well, if ſoe, &amp; they be deſpiſed in deed, lett it be examined vvhether they have not brought the contempt upon their ovvne heades? are not ſome
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:15958:20"/>of them reeds ſhaken vvith the vvind; &amp; like vvethercocks turned round? have they not in one day preached earneſtly for reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; in another againſt it? in one daie practized contrarie to the ceremonies, &amp; in another perſecuted their people for not joyning vvith them in uſe of them? have not others of them ſubſcribed (as themſelues confeſſe) they knovv not to vvhat? and in deed have manie of them ſoe much as read, much leſſe conſidered thoſe fyve bookes to vvhich they have ſubſcribed? profeſſe not manie of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they vvill not read theſe bookes, becauſe they vvill not be troubled vvith it? have not diuerſe others, vvith as little vvit as honeſtie gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen out, they vvill not looſe their cocks of barley, there peaſe ricks, their rie and vvheate ſheaves for ſuch trifles? and vvhat ever their gifts be, vvhen they preach; ſtuffe they not their ſermons full of gt. &amp; latin, Fathers &amp; Fables, outcries &amp; exclamations ag: Calvin, Beza, Cartvvrite, Puritans &amp;c. calling for the ſvvord of the Mag: &amp; crying crucifige; ſo making the heart of the rightuous ſadd, and ſtrengthninge the hand of the vvicked? all vvhich conſidered, no great merveile, is it, though they have not ſuch place in the hearts of the forwarder ſort, &amp; reuerence from them as they expecte, nether in deed ought they if M. D. ſaie true in his former ſermon. But if he meane it of ſuch Miniſters as being of good gifts (though con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable) doe in Godly purenes and ſimplicity according to the grace receyved, execute their miniſtrie; (of which ſort vve knovv and acknovvledg manie amonge us) I vvill be ſo bold as tell him that the firſt part of this ſecond imputation is a vvell knovvne ſlan der &amp; the frequentinge of their miniſterie by the beſt Chriſtians in citie and cuntrie, &amp; that vvith traveyle thereto 2.3.4.5.6.8.10. myles at a time, &amp; contributing to their maintenance, doth prove it ſo to be. As for <hi>their incouraging of their admired Miniſters to ſtand out,</hi> therein, vvhat doe they but their duties? ought they not to deale ſo vvith the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that they maie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynue &amp; perſeyer in their good cauſe; &amp; not for loue of meede, &amp; feare of need, goe back, ſell the truth &amp; vvreck
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:15958:21"/>their conſciences ſhall it not be their ſin to diſcourage them, &amp; by neglecting them to occaſion or driue them to Apoſtacie? &amp; muſt it needs argue, that therefore they eſteme not the Miniſteries false word their chife treaſure, but had rather want the foood of their ſouls, then not to enjoye their fancies &amp;c. as he ſaith? verely, how falſe this is, manie places wittnes, where the people yeilding and paying their tithes, to their Parſons and Curates who are little bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thon theeves and robbers; doe notwithſtanding to their great charge mainteine preachers that conforme, and otherwiſe to their great trouble, charge &amp; perill, traveil many milles to heare them: In his third Charge as out of a murdering peece, he ſhooteth all kinds of ſhott, knyves, daggers, bullet, hayleshott and all, as if he would kill all afore him: but in truth in the diſcharge of it, it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coyleth yea reboundeth upon himſelf &amp; his. Firſt, ſaith he, <hi>they place the height of religion in diſconformitie,</hi> how much more truely may we ſaie it of him and the Bbs. (diuerſe of them) who place it in conformitie, the ſubſtance in ceremonie, the forme &amp; that which giueth the very being to it, in formalitie. Doe we forſake the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies where the ceremonies are uſed? refuſe we to comunicate with the Miniſters that uſe them? doe not they withhold the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters from preaching and adminiſtring the ſacraments that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe not, &amp; conforme not? and which is more, doe they not ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend, excom: &amp; cutt of from the Church for want of it? doth not their Canon decree ſuſpenſion, for Miniſter and people both, that conforme not to that one geſture, of kneeling to receyve the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per? Secondly he telleth us, <hi>they turne zeale into faction, combine them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues into a divided brotherhood &amp;c.</hi> Cruelly, diſdeynefully and ſpite fully ſpeaketh he againſt the rightuous, &amp; the accuſers heart know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth how innocent they are herein, lett him name us the man that hath his hand in this treſpaſſe, as not to eſteme them brethren that conforme, or to refuſe ſociety with them for it: doe we not as Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carp
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:15958:21"/>and Anicetus, Policrates and Victor, communicate one with another, though we diſſent one of us from another in ſome cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies as they did in other? But as he and others write, ſoe they ſpeak and preach, and ſeek by ſuch calumniations to eſtrang from us, yea to inflame his Magiſties heart, &amp; the hearts of his Nobles, Iudges, Iuſtices and people againſt us. Lett him remember what Iulian once ſayd, <hi>ſi accuſaſſe ſufficiat, quis crit innocens?</hi> yf it be enough to accuſe, who ſhal be innocent? not Moſes, not Ezra, not Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, not the prophets, not Chriſt himſelf, nor his Apoſtles, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all whom this verie ſlander laie. And whereas through theſe &amp; ſuch lik ſlanders our Oppoſites have ſoe preveyled againſt us vvith our <hi>Soueraigne,</hi> (as others by the like did againſt <hi>Chriſostom</hi>
               <note n="(q)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon cont. Apol: Sem. part 2. p.</hi> 210.</note> with <hi>Arcadius,</hi>) that they which have petitioned for us, (as others did for him) are now, as then, reproached as troublers of the ſtate; and the more we are ſued for, the hardlyer both we &amp; our freinds are uſed; I wiſh the accuſers, M. D. eſpecially, to withdrawe their hands out of this treſpaſſe, leſte they dravve much blood upon them, &amp; the Lord look upon it &amp; require it. Thirdly, <hi>they turne,</hi> ſaith he. <hi>Godly conferences into bitter invectives ag: Bbs. &amp; odious cenſures of ſuch as they call formaliſts &amp;c.</hi> Yf we conferre &amp; diſpute of the diſcipline and uſe of the ceremonies ſo urged, what merveil? would not any one gladly ſee whether Chriſt &amp; his Apoſtles euer ordeyned ſuch yokes to be layd upon the necks of his diſciples, by ſuch Taskma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters as plague their purſes by exceſſive fees and exactions, wearie their bodies with longe journeyes to and ſro their courts 500 my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les in a yeare; tyrannize ouer their ſoules with Canons and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, ſett thick and threefold as ſnares and trapps to ketch in, and to that end talk and conferre about them, that if at be the yoak of Chriſt, they maie willingly beare it, if not, as it is not, gladly and by good meanes be ridd of it? but that they <hi>turne all their ſtudie of the ſcriptures in ſuch diſputaitons &amp;c.</hi> is alſo vntrue: and if there be a fault
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:15958:22"/>committed, it is in ſtudying and conferring of theſe matters to lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, rather then too much. The accuſation in deed lieth upon the men of his ovvne ſyde, vvho for Godly conferences, orderly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations, and graue ſermons, be (many of them) nothing elſe, for the moſte part, but make odious invectiues, giue forth vnjuſt cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, ſlanderous reproaches, filling pulpitts, benches, conſiſtories, &amp; forniſhing printers preſſes with little other ſtoffe, but ſuch and ſuch falſe imputations of combination, faction, ſedition, puritani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, &amp; odious termes of ſchiſmatikes, humoriſts, refractaries &amp;c. &amp; what elſe can we look for, at other mens hands, vvhen M. D. pen is full of them? Fourthly he blameth them for <hi>being ignorant in the Catechiſm, &amp; yet to ſtand upon theſe things.</hi> A fault in deed: &amp; if thoſe vvhom he counteth the forvvarder ſort be ignorant of the Catechiſm, vvhat are the backvvardder? but vvhere is the fault? is it not in ſuch as ſhould inſtructe them better; but diſdeine to teach the Catechiſm, it is ſoe baſe a ſervice; or if they teach it, doe it but for fashion, even to pronounce a fewe words without vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding more like parrats &amp; popingaies then otherwiſe? But lett us heare his laſte ſlander in this 3. charge, where he ſaith, <hi>they confine their charitie to their divided brotherhood,</hi> as if they miniſtred to the neceſſitie of no other, but thoſe that are as forward as themſelues. The vvhich is ſoe notoriouſly falſe in the knovvledge of all men, that all men maie vvonder, hovv it ſlipped from his pen. Yf men, vvho by the labours of the Miniſters are brought to the knovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of the truth, conuerted to God, &amp; confirmed in good, have shevved mercie &amp; compaſſion to thoſe Miniſters, their vvyves &amp; children, vvrongefully deprived of their lyvings, &amp; expoſed to po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>verrie, or vvreck of conſcience: have they done othervviſe then the Lord requireth of them &amp; the Saints have practized?
<note n="(r)" place="margin">1 <hi>theſ.</hi> 5.12.13. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.13.14 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 6 6.</note> what mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth M. D. eie then, to be evill becauſe others are good? is he gree<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ved that vve liue, that there are yet ſome fevve lefte to ſeek the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:15958:22"/>vvealth of Iſraell? vvisheth he vvith Caligula, that vve had all but one neck, &amp; in his hands a ſvvord to cutt it of at one ſtrok; that he cannot paſſe by in ſilence, or ſpeak vvith charitie of that benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence that is miniſtred to us? or doth his mouth crave it of his pen, have vve too much &amp; he to little, vvould he have part vvith us? yf ſoe, vve vvill ſpeak for him. But the truth is, this imputation muſt goe home from vvhence it cam; even to himſelf and others of his ſyd, vvhoſe charitie, if it vvere not confyned to their divided bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therhood of conformitans, vvhy crie they out upon thoſe that ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour us, &amp; ſpeak evill upon the lyving &amp; the dead both, for giving to us; condemninge it as given to impious uſes? yea vvhat elſe mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth the taking of that from us, vvhich is giuen to us, and beſtovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> formaliſts? Lord lay not this ſin to their charge.</p>
            <p>Thus much to the particulars in his <hi>3.</hi> head, the fourth follovveth, vvherein he chargeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be <hi>danger ouſly vnthankfull to God for the contynuanc of his goſpell, our peace &amp; proſperitie, &amp; to take on, even no we that we have almoſt we can deſyer, as if we had nothing, &amp; like way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward children, having that which is fitt for us, to caſte it a waie, becauſe we have not what we fancie beſides.</hi> Lett him that thinketh he ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, take heed leaſt he fall; &amp; being dovvne, full &amp; fall he knovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not vvhither; men that have knovvne M. D. mind in the daies that are paſt: vvould hardly have thought, he could have fallen thus farre, as to ſaie that vve <hi>have almoſt whatſoeuer we can deſyre, yea that which is fitt for us:</hi> vve vvill praie for him: and to this charge of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfullnes more bitter then gall, and burninge then the coales of Iuniper, (not pleading vvith God, before vvhom vve muſt fall dovvne and like the duſt and confeſſe that vve are in finitely guilty) I anſvvere, and vvish him, firſt to remember hovv he chargeth us vvith all evill,
<note n="(s)" place="margin">ingra tum. qui dixerit, omnia mala dixerit.</note> in charging us to be vnthankfull &amp; praie him to call to mind vvhat he hath read in the holy ſcriptures, ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers &amp; heathen vvriters in condemnation of vnthankfullnes, and then ſecondly I ſafe to him,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:15958:23"/>as the <hi>Orator</hi> ſayd to <hi>Erucius,</hi> accuſing, <hi>Sextus Roſcius</hi> for the death of his Father. <hi>In hoc tanto tam atroci, tam ſingulari maleficio, quibus tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem M. D. argumentis, accuſatorem vti cenſes oportere.</hi> Oh M. D. you that thus accuſe us, think with your ſelf, what good arguments you had need have, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>vince us of ſoe vile an evill. Giue me leave to plead the caſe a little with you I praie, yf we be vnthankfull be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we are not content with all things as they novv ſtand, but wiſhe a further reformation, &amp; deſyre that God maie be more glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rified, his goſpell further propagated, his people better edifyed, the walles of Sion builded, and Babel, how golden &amp; glorious ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, ruinated &amp; razed to the ground, till no one ſtone their of be lefte upon another; we are not aſhamed, but will carrie this note and marke as a diamand upon our fortheads:
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6 22.</note> yea as <hi>David</hi> ſaid to <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chol, I will yet be more vile;</hi> ſoe ſaie we to M. D. yf this be vnthank fullnes, we will yet be more vnthankfull. we acknowledge the wonderfull patience and longe ſuffering of our good and gratious God, in bearing with us hitherto; we magnifie the exceeding ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of his mercie, in viſitinge us, with ſo manie &amp; merveilous de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liuerances: we joie &amp; rejoyce with ioye vnſpeakable in the glorious light of the goſpell, which (notwithſtanding the great ecclipſe ſoe lately made) ſhineth yet in manie places as cleare as the ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at noone daie, the confortable light wherof, we eſteeme as the life of our life. Nether are we vnmindefull of Gods goodnes towards us in that outward peace and proſperity which we injoye vnder the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerment of our dread ſovereigne, the breath of our noſtrels, vnder the ſhadowe of whoſe winges next vnder God, we aknowledge our lives preſerved amonge the heathen: we bleſſe God for him, &amp; ſhall neuer ceaſe to ſaie <hi>God ſave the Kinge;</hi> what then? are we not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding vnthankfull, becauſe we deſire to drinke more plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully, even our fill of the ſvveet cupp of theſe mercies and that God would fulfill all the good pleaſure of his goodnes upon us &amp;
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:15958:23"/>oue poſteritie? I trow not: <hi>eſt ingenui &amp; liberalis animi, cui-multum debeas, ei plus veldebere:</hi> it is no vnthankfullnes to deſyre to be more indebted to him, to whom we owe much already. But ſee, hovv M. D. taxeth all the ſervants of God, high &amp; lowe, from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining of the vvourld almoſte, to this daie, vvith vnthankfullnes; if this be vnthankfullnes: vvould David lett the ark alone vvhere Saul his predeceſſour left it? did Salomon lett it reſt, vvhere David his Father left it? did not Ichoſaphat lifte up his heart to the vvaies of the Lord? took he not a vvaie the high places and groves from out of Iudah, and reformed he not more then his predeceſſours, yea more then Aſa his Father had done before him? did not Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah throvv dovvne the high places, vvhich Iehoſaphat lefte ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding? did not Ioſias ouer turne many things, vvhich Hezekiah threvv not dovvne? vvhat ment the cheife Fathers and Ancients, Preiſts and Levites after their returne from captivity vvhen they ſavve the foundation of the temple layd, becauſe it vvas not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſvverable to the former; to vveep, I ſaie to vveepe vvhen others laughed for ioie? vvhy did Nehemia buyld the vvalles of Ieruſalem, perfit that vvhich Ezra began, and reformed the feaſt of Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles better then all his predeceſſours hovv Godly and zealous ſo ever? vvherefore did the Lords prophets preſſe a further reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon the Kings follovving, vvhatſoeuer reformation their predeceſſors had made before them? vvhat ment they? vvere they all vnthankfull? Lett us come dovvne lovver; <hi>An non perfecit Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinus quod Philippus ìam ceperat,</hi>
               <note n="(t)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ceſar Barai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. An</hi> 227.</note> did not Conſtantine perfit vvhat Philipp began; did not Theodoſius
<note n="(u)" place="margin">
                  <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od ore Hiſt. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>Ca.</hi> 20</note> goe forvvards vvith the reformation vvhere Conſtantine lefie? ſee the ſtoryes. To co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e lovver yet, vvhat vvill M. D. ſaie to thoſe vvorthey lights and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Martyrs? to Father Latimer? vvho reſted not vvith the refor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mation in K. Henrie the S. daies but parſvvaded K. Edvvard to a further; to Hooper and Bucer?
<note n="(x)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bucer in cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra Ca.</hi> 12</note> hovv not content vvith the firſt
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:15958:24"/>purging of the leiturgie by K. Edward, gaue him not over till he had purifyed it the ſecond time, as the ſecond edition therof ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: to our late ſovereigne Lady now bleſſed? who reformed di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe things lefte by her worthy brother; to Bb. Iewell, Bentham, Pilkinton &amp; others? who never preſented omnia bene to her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtie, as M. D. here doth to all the world, vvhere he ſaith, <hi>we have what is fitt for us, almost what we can deſire.</hi> Conclud, if vve be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanfull, are not all theſe? if dangerouſly vnthankfull; vvhat is M. D. himſelf? vvho in his ſermon before named, (vvhich I vviſh were read euery morning to our Bbs. next their hearts) contenteth not himſelf with the miniſtery amonge us as it novv ſlandeth, but cenſureth ſharplie &amp; rightly, that ignorant idle &amp; ſcandalous Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie, vvhich poſſeſſeth agreat parte of the land, &amp; vve dſyre maie poſſeſſe no parte of it. The truth is, that this crime of vnthankfull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes here caſt upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> us, belongeth properly to others vvho are at eaſe in Sion, abondantly provided for, gorgiouſly clothed, fare delici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, invent to themſelues inſtruments of delight, rovve in their barges, rid in their coches from houſe to houſe at pleaſure, think it time to repaire &amp; buyld their ovvne hovvſes, to ſeele their cham<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bers &amp;c. more princelik then preiſtlik: and yet ſaie it is not time to buyld the Lors houſe, or repaire ought that is amiſſe therin, naie condemne them of dangerous vnthankfullnes, that vvill bringe one ſtone tovvards it, or ſo much as vviſhe vvell to it: doe you ſoe revvard the L. ye houſe of Iſraell?.</p>
            <p>Thus as length are vve come to the ende of his fourth charge: in his fyfte, he accuſeth us, <hi>to grow wanton in religion, through ſpirituall pride, not caring for the heavenly foode of our ſoules, vnleſſe we maie have our owne ſauce, preferring the ceremonie and circumſtance of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion before the ſubſtance:</hi> vpon vvhoſe ſhoulders this taxe lieth hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vieſt, theirs or ours, lett the vvorld judge: vve for our parts deſire
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:15958:24"/>no ſauce of our ovvne, but vve utterly diſlike the popiſh Cookes, that have devyſed ſauces to make our religion ſavour and have a taſte vvith carnall appetites; and vve take no pleaſure in thoſe po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh patchers, vvho marre our religious ſober &amp; chaſte attire, and aſſaie to make her of a grave and ſober matrone, like a masking mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; and this vve count and that moſt juſtlie, ſpirituall prid and vvantonnes in religion. But to proue it, he chargeth 3. particulars upon us concerning the vvord, publik praier, and the ſacraments. In the firſt, he blameth us: firſt, <hi>for that we will not heare as he ſaith, a ſermon made at a funerall, be it neuer ſo proſitable;</hi> ſecondly, <hi>that by our good will we would heare none that is conformable, or if we doe, it is with preiudice, and making the word ineffectuall to us, we ſaye his gifts are decayed, his preaching is without power &amp;c.</hi> both vvhich are meere ſlanders. Concerninge the former, the truth is, that many both Godly and learned, conſidering the originall of funerall ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons from vvhence they cam; the ende for vvhich for the moſte parte they are novv obſerved, to vvit, the honor of the dead, and enriching of the preacher; and then hovv partially and vvith vvhat reſpect of parſons they are novv performed, for the riche not for the poore; &amp; laſtly, hovv the preacher for his hire, as <hi>M. Dearing</hi> ſaith,
<note n="(y)" place="margin">in his ſermons on the hebrews.</note> 
               <hi>with a black mouth and a headlong tongue,</hi> bleſſeth the dead, calleth the niggard liberall; the eruell Nymrods and mightie hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the rightuous, myld and gentle parſonages, vvhoremongers and Adulterers, chaſte Ioſephs: popiſh ſuperſticious and profane parſons, true and religious goſpellers; and all this in their eates, vvho knovv they lie for advantage, and to pleaſe the frinds and kindred of the dead, vvhereby much offence often commeth to the hearers. Godly and learned men I ſaic conſidering theſe things,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:15958:25"/>it is no mervell they have no great affection to ſuch ſermons but to ſaie, they utterly refuſe to heare any be they never ſo profitable is a flatt vntruth. His ſecond is alſo a verie ſlander, as in parte hath already bin ſhewed, where the firſt breach thereof vvas hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; ſecondly vvhere he chargeth us, <hi>to heare thoſe that we doe heare with preiudice,</hi> he ſhevveth himſelf againe as ofte before, to be an in truder of himſelf into another mans co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience; thirdly vvhether vve or others <hi>make the word more vneffectuall to us:</hi> lett the effects ſhevve; fourthly yf any charge ſuch as have co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>formed, <hi>with decaie of gifts, &amp; loſse of the power of their miniſlery vniustly,</hi> I will not juſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fye the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in it: but they that have eyes to ſee, maie ſee it is too true, in too manie at this daie, &amp; if they ſee it not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, it is their owne blindnes. But to paſſe by the like ſla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders in the reſt of thoſe vvords, lett us come to his 2 charge vvhich concerneth praier; vvhere he ſaith, <hi>that if lawe did not compell us, we had rather be at no publi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, then at thoſe ſeett forth by authority, or if we be preſent, we ioine not with the congregation.</hi> In deed, vvhere publique praiers are read by ſuch ſeely Curates, as can doe nothing but reade, &amp; then alſo ſlub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred and poſted over, that they maie poſte to ſome other place for the like ſervice:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heſra.</hi> 46.</note> ſuch parſons being no preiſts to the Lord, nor per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>forminge any ſervice in him and for him; it is not much to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned in the forwarder ſort, that they are greived thereat, and joyne no further then lavve compelleth them. Nay I vvonder they can come to them at all; ſeing manie of the vulgar ſort, that have little ſavour of grace in them, diſtaſte both the Sayers &amp; their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, &amp; vvould not joine vvith them, vvere they not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto. But vvhere publique praier is read by any Miniſter of God, I perſvvad my ſelf, M. D. cannot make good this charge upon any one of them. Lett us therefore heare his 3 cenſure which concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the ſacraments vvhere he ſaith, <hi>we had rather, if we might chooſe, not have our childe baptized, then that the croſſe in baptiſme
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:15958:25"/>should be uſed; and not receyve the communion, then receyve kneeling &amp;c.</hi> For anſwere wherevnto, in generall, lett it be obſerved how againe he ſitteth in the conſcience of his brother &amp; judgeth him to deſyre the ſacraments as they are now adminiſtred, not of conſcience to Gods ordinance; but onely to aveyd puniſhment; Secondly, concerninge baptiſme, lett him tell us, whether he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf that now yeldeth ſoe willing to the croſſe in baptiſme; would yeld as readily <hi>to oile, creame, ſalt, ſpittle</hi> &amp; the ſetting on of the croſſ on the lipps, cies, care and aſwell as on the forhead? yf not? lett him not blame us then, yf we would not willinglie have our chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren croſſed, none of the other are more evill then this, as that learned treatiſſe of the ceremo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ies, ſheweth
<note n="(z)" place="margin">Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasticall diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeagainſt ſymboliz<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing with Antich. &amp;c.</note>. But that any vvould rather their children ſhould not be baptized at all, then croſſed, is vntrue, we have learned, that however the Miniſter ſinneth in making it, the parent that proteſteth againſt it, ſinneth not in de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyring the ſacrament, &amp; for his credit ſake, lett him name us ſome fewe that keep their children vnbaptized becauſe of it. As for kneeling at the inſtant of receyving the bread and wine in the L. ſupper: ſeing it is ſoe ſufficiently proved to be vnlawfull both be fore and ſince this ſermon, by a certeine Diſpute of that ſubject. M. D. mought have forborne, &amp; I hope will hereafter forbeare the raxing of us for refuſing it, eſpecially till that <hi>Diſpute</hi> be ſoundly an ſvvered &amp; confuted. Thus much for the imputations laid upon al Chriſtians in generall, of the forwarder ſort as he calleth them. Now it followeth in particular of them that ſett forth the book in titled the <hi>Modeſt Ofer &amp;c.</hi> whom he challengeth, to have publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed <hi>diverſe aſſertions</hi> which he calleth <hi>ſchiſmaticall novelties, new found affections, vndigeſled fancies,</hi> the principall <hi>wherof were neuer heard of in the Church of God aboue</hi> 1600 <hi>yeares after Chriſt, the which, yf they were established, would breed horrible confuſions, and yet ſo vehe mently urged by them, that ſeperation is to be made from all thoſe Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:15958:26"/>which admitt them not; and if they be not granted, they ſee not how our ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>paration from the Church of Rome can be iustifyed, and doe offer that if the Preiſts and Ieſuites can ſatisfye them concerninge their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, they will be reconciled to the ſea of Rome &amp;c.</hi> Theſe &amp; ſuch like speaches chargeth he upon them, and in the laſt page challen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geth all Godly &amp; learned Miniſt, that <hi>proteſt not against them and diſſavow them, but ſuffer the people to receyve them.</hi> For anſwere wherunto, firſt this I maie ſay, that the publishers of thoſe aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions have hitherto (as appeareth by that their modeſt offer not yet accepted) bin more ready to prove them to be no ſuch ſchiſma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticall novelties, new found aſſertions, new undigeſted fancies, as he calleth them, then he or any of his ſide are, to make good this charge. Secondly, how confidently ſoever they avouch them; yet in the conſcience of M. D. himſelf &amp; the reſt of his ſyde, (ſuch as are indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t at leſte) they are as farre (if not further) from joining with the Papiſts as ſome Prelates &amp; their Proctors, utterly abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their abhominable idolatries, deteſtable hereſies, vaine devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces &amp; inventions, ſuperſtitions, rites &amp; ceremonies ſtollen from Iewes or Gentiles, unfeynedly hateing that whore of Babylon, that ſea of Antichriſt, that mother of fornication, died read with the bloud of the Saints; yea deteſting head &amp; taile, roote &amp; branch of poperie, being in deed of the nomber, of thoſe (whom Bb. Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cont. Apol. Sem. pa.</hi> 22.</note> commendeth,) <hi>who are ſoe farr from admitting the full doze of Popish haereſies, that by no meanes they can diieſte one dram of their ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies;</hi> and of thoſe, <hi>who</hi> (as D. Fulk
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Retent. againſt Briſtow pa.</hi> 98.</note> ſaith) <hi>abhorre whatſoever hath but a shewe of poperie.</hi> Novv they being ſuch men in deed, and that in the conſciences of our adverſaries, though they in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of the truth of thoſe aſſertions, reſolutelie deliver, that if our Prelates can mainteine their dignities, preheminence &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jorite of rule, vvhich novv they exerciſe over us, to be jure divino, and that there be Churches Dioceſan, Provinciall &amp; nationall,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:15958:26"/>founded in the vvord: it vvill then follovv by as good reaſon, that there is a Church univerſall, and ſoe one univerſall Paſtor to be ſett over all; vvhich being the ordinance and inſtitution of God, is not to be rejected for the faults of men: M. D. might have ſpared theſe reproaches, &amp; ſpent his ſpeach and pen much better, in ſhevv<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing hovv the conſequence is not good, &amp; that the one ought to be receyved, the other in no ſort to be admitted; ſoe had he done God &amp; his Reader good ſervice, &amp; his brethren the leſſe vvro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge, vvhich is ſoe much the greater, for that diverſe of theſe imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons vvere removed by their ovvne anſvvere in that <hi>modeſt offer</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>In their anſwere to the</hi> 11 <hi>oppoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pag</hi> 38</note> &amp; the reſte anſvvered by vvord of mouth before the high Commi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſſion at Lambith, before M. D. eyther preached or printed this Sermon, yea the aſſertions themſelves proved in a former booke of M. H. I. for any anſvvere &amp; proofe they have yet made to the contrarie.</p>
            <p>As for his challenging of all them vvho <hi>diſſavovve not thoſe aſſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions, &amp; proteſt not against them,</hi> I vvill onely aſke him, vvhat he meaneth to beate himſelf and the reſte of his ſyde ſoe ſoundly. It is vvell knovvne vvhat corrupt and unſound doctrines have bin lately preached &amp; printed here in England, as <hi>that the ſcriptures co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine not all thinges neceſſarie to be knovvne to ſalvation; that they are not the onely rule of all good and evill in the actions of men; that it is not to be inquired whether Chriſt be in the Sacrament by Conſubstantiation or Tranſubſtantiation, &amp; that it can no waies hinder or further us howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it ſtand.</hi> Whereof ſee M. Hooker
<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>pa</hi> 88. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>pa</hi> 122. <hi>lib.</hi> 5 <hi>pa.</hi> 176.</note>. <hi>That the keeping of one daie in ſeven is ceremoniall, &amp; obſerved novv de iure humano onely,</hi> ſee D. Hovvſons ſerm. upon Pſ. 118, page 20. <hi>That Divorces are a</hi> thoro <hi>onely &amp; not a</hi> vinculo, <hi>&amp; that the innocent partie after divorce, maie not marry againe.</hi> Theſ. Edit. Oxon. Anno 1602. The vvhich (vvith manie more concerning <hi>Chriſts deſſention into hell; the ſtate of Infants that die unbaptized,</hi> &amp; ſuch like) are not approved for Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicall truthes; vvhy then doth MASTER DOCTOR,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:15958:27"/>yea and the Prelates and the reſte of their Chapleins, proteſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, diſſavowe them? Why are the people ſuffred to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyve them as oracles? Thus much for his ſecond heade and the ſeverall branches of it; lett us now examine the third, and both the exhortations in it. The firſt is to unitie and peace, layd downe in many words, the breife whereof is, <hi>that we would fynde argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to reunite our ſelves, &amp; yf the proofes he hath brought in his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon overweye our reaſons, we would ingeniouſly acknowledg the truth.</hi> And becauſe he thinks, that feare of diſcredit maie hinder it, he taketh it awaie by three reaſons; firſt, <hi>from the remembrance of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s comon frailty, which is ſubiect to over ſight: Secondly from the revere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d opinion worthily conceyved of M. Calvin, Beza and other Divines. Thirdly, from the conceite of the good effects of the Diſcipline deſired, &amp; evill of the eſtablished;</hi> In this firſt exhortation I moſt willing joyne with him, and doe earneſtly praie him, and charge him in the L. as he will anſwere it at that laſt and dreadfull daie; that he would in deed ſeek the peace of Sion, and be as deſyrous to uſe meanes to reunite himſelf and the reſte to us, and the reformed Churches; as he hath bin in this Sermon overbuſy in ſeeking rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſons to disjoine himſelf and others from us, and them; and that he would weigh in the ballance of an unpartiall judgment the anſweres brought to his proofes, and if he fynde them to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weigh his reaſons, he would give glorie to God, by acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging ingenuouſly ſoe profitable, and as theſe tymes are, ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie a truth. And that according to his owne doctrine in his former Sermon, of the great neceſſity of the ſound and ſyncere preaching of the Goſpell, he would by all meanes labour, that it maie have free paſſage, that the people which periſh for want of knowledge, maie be taught the vvaie of ſalvation, that all true labourers in the word and doctrine, maie have the double honot he ſpeaketh of, &amp; be cheerished as bees in the hyve; &amp; that all Loy terers maie be chaſed from it as drones; that vaine titles maie not
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:15958:27"/>anſwere for painfull offices &amp; duties: that garments, compleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts &amp; ſhadowes maie not be preſſed and preferred before ſubſtances, that the hearts of the rightuous maie be made no longer ſadd for vvelldoinge, nor the hands of the vvicked confermed &amp; ſtrenght<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in evill. This is the ready waie to true peace &amp; vnitie, by this meanes vve ſhall meet togither in one, vnited &amp; revnited one to another: godlines vvill floriſh, athiſm &amp; papiſme vvill be putt to flight, the popiſh hope &amp; expectation of a change vvill be cruſhed, the mouthes that ſpeak proud things wilbe ſtopped, God vvilbe our God, our Sheild, our Buckler, our Caſtle and Defence, vve shalbe his people, &amp; shall not need to feare any mallice of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaryes hovv many, hovv mighty, how cruelly &amp; malliciouſly, ſett &amp; bent againſt us ſoever they be: much leſſe the feare of diſcre ditt he ſpeaketh of. Where becauſe as it ſeemeth, he judgeth of our eſtate, by the feeling he hath of his ovvne pulſt, it shall not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe to returne him home his ovvne reaſons vvith exchange of a fevv words: and therefore doe tell him, firſt he shall not need to feare diſcreditt, by making open acknovvledgment of his errors, diſcouered in this anſvvere &amp; the hurt he hath done thereby: For the beſt maie erre, &amp; it is a work of grace fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God &amp; creditt vvith men to confeſſe them. Yf it vvere a diſcreditt: yet it shall be good for him vvith Ierom <hi>plus conſcienciae, quam nomini deferre,</hi> to reſpect his conſcience more then his creditt. The reverent opinion vve have vvorthily conceyved of thoſe vvorthy divines, hath moved us in deed the rather to imbrace the diſcipline vve ſtand for: &amp; vve had good reaſon for it ſeing God hath bleſſed them ſoe exceeding abundantly, in all ſpirituall knovvledge and vnderſtanding, that (their &amp; our aduerſaries being Iudges) <hi>they are found admirably ſound &amp; orthodoxall in the ſubſtanciall pointes of religion.</hi> Yett have vve not ſoe relied upon their creditts, as not to ſearch into, &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine upon vvhat grounds they &amp; vve ſtand as too manie of the other ſyd, vvho in their ſimplicitie (preſuminge upon the vviſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:15958:28"/>and ſynceritie of the Bbs. whom they ſuppoſed would require no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but what they might ſafely yeld vnto) have relied on their creditts &amp; putt to their hands &amp; names, they knew not to what; that fault therefore which in this ſecond reaſon he extenuareth in us, is greater in them &amp; had the more need be confeſſed by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. As for the effects of both which in his 3. reaſon he ſpeaketh of, we muſt needs acknowledge they have had their effects vvith us.</p>
            <p>The vnſpeakeable good, vvhich that diſcipline, that he calleth <hi>newe</hi> &amp; vve <hi>olde</hi> &amp; <hi>ancient,</hi> hath yelded to the Churches imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceing it, the vvhich alſo, vve are perſvvaded, it vvill affoard us vvhenever vve receyve it, cannot but vvork effectually in us an earneſt deſyer &amp; longing after it; as the manifold corruptions in doctrine &amp; manners, taxes, troubles and vexations for vvell doing, vvhether ariſing from the perſonall defaults of the gouernours, or nature of the gouernment it ſelf; (not here to be diſputed of) but cleaving ſoe inſeperablie to it, that ſoe longe as the one remeineth vve cannot expecte any freedome from the other; hath made the Iſrael of God to grone vnto him for eaſe &amp; deliuerance from it.</p>
            <p>As for the horrible confuſions, vvhich vvould inevitably follovve if <hi>the diſcipline</hi> (as he ſarcaſtically calleth it) <hi>of the ne weſt edition</hi> vvere eſtabliſhed, vvhereby he vvould leſſen the corruptions of our tymes; as he ſpeaketh of that he knovveth not: ſoe vvhen he telleth us vvhat they are, he ſhall receyve his anſvvere. Thus much for his firſt exhortation, his ſecond follovveth, to vvit, that in cauſe his arguments in this ſermon, <hi>through our preiudice &amp; partial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity ſeeme light to us, and we yeild not to them; that then our anſweres maie be diſtinctly applyed to euery argument in order, with pregnant &amp; demonſtrative proofes, &amp; then he will acknowledge his error, onely he deſyreth Chriſtian &amp; modeſte dealinge, not ſuch as is in that book called, the Chriſtian &amp; modeſt offer.</hi> Wherein, (to paſſe by the repeating of ſome things before ſpoken of, here againe mentioned, &amp; namely the ſlander of Chriſt diſcipline, in ſaying <hi>it was neuer heard of till
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:15958:28"/>now of late, &amp; that our gouernment by Bbs. hath bin perpetually obſerued in the Church euer ſince the Apoſtles tymes,</hi> the falſhood of both vvhich pointes hath bin &amp; ſhalbe at large diſcouered) vve have 3 things to be obſerved: firſt a diſyre of an anſvvere; 2. the conditions required; 3. a promyſe. Yf vve turne not vvith him, his deſyre is, vve vvould returne him an anſvvere, <hi>a diſtincte anſwer to all his arguments in order.</hi> So doe the Doctors of Oxford in their anſvvere to the peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the 1000 Miniſters; ſo doth G. P. in his laſt book, vvhere he vndertaketh the anſvvering of all that can be ſayd in theſe cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. And M. Hooker in his preface before his firſt book of politikes, yea Bb. Barlovve himſelf preaching upon Acts 20 28 for the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment eſtabliſhed, much of the ſame that M. D. doth in this ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon, in his epiſtle before it, profeſſeth that if there shall an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſvvere be made therevnto <hi>with modeſty and learning, nothing shalbe more wellcome,</hi> &amp; that, <hi>to avouch &amp; make it good;</hi> that the ſayd epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copall calling is vnlavvfull, <hi>were a labour worthy the traveil &amp; much deſyred of the Bbs.</hi> All vvhich is done, if not by the appointment &amp; commandment of the Bbs. themſelues; yet by their conſent &amp; vvith their good allovvance, their bookes being ſeene &amp; allovved, &amp; ſome of them commended &amp; commanded to be published, as they printe themſelues in their firſt pages. Wherein lett it be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered hovv injuriouſly vve are dealt vvith: firſt they deny us all meanes to publish our anſwers, taking from us the liberty of the preſſe, &amp; punishing printer &amp; thoſe whom they ſuſpect for authors, not ſparing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that will not bettaie the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: whoſoeuer conſidereth theſe dealings maie juſtly ſuſpect, the Bbs &amp; their Chapleines are combyned togither, the one to ſett ſnares &amp; drawe us into them, the other to catch and crushe us: maie I not ſaie to them as <hi>Ierom</hi>
               <note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron. Au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>guſt. Tom.</hi> 2.</note> once ſayd, why are we blamed for writinge, is the fault in us or in your ſelues that provoke us, are we not compelled to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend our ſelues in our juſt proceedings? you have brought us to a fayre paſſe, yf we holde our peace, you holde us guilty; yf we anſwere, we are judged enemyes, as Ierom was, &amp; punished for anſwering as Ieto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was not. A hard condition of each ſyd, but of the two, we will chooſe the eaſyer,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:15958:29"/>rather then by ſilence to betraye the truth, by juſte apologie, what euer it coſte us, to mainteine it, yf you will have us to deſiſte from anſweringe; doe not you propound againſt us, laye you aſyde your ſwords, we will ſoone laie by our targetts: otherwiſe yf though you firſt provok us to ſpeak and then puniſh us; know you it is not the feare of puniſhment that shall fright us, the truth, which is the life of our life, is more deare vnto us. Thus much for his deſyre or challenge, his conditions followe and they are two. In the firſt he requireth that <hi>we diſtinctly apply our anſweres to euery of his arguments in order, with proofs pregnant and demonſtratyve.</hi> Which I acknowledge but reaſon; and had he dealt ſoe with us in his ſermon, we should have giuen him no anſwere: but his carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing awaie the matter in tryvmph, with diſcourſes, gueſſes, fancies, counterfeit writers, wittneſſes borne out of oue time, not old e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough by 2 or 3 hundred yeares (ſome of them) to giue wittnes to his cauſe, his forced interpretations of ſcriptures and Fathers devy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of purpos, and vvith great ſtreme of vvit, to putt by the truth, his equiuocations, frivolous and looſe collections, vvherof vve have good ſtore in his ſermon, (as their anſwere shall shevve) none of vvhich vvill beare a ſyllogiſme, nor abyd the hammering vpon the right anvyle: theſe courſes I ſaye can vve not allovv for proofes pregnant and demonſtratyve. As for this anſvvere, I refer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re it to the Reader to judge vvhether the demonſtrations therein, be not ſound, the proofes pregnant, and the arguments ſtrongely grounded upon the ſcripture, vvith plaine interpretations, &amp; ſuch as have conſent, not of ſome fevve olde and nevve vvriters onely: but almoſt of all divines ſound and orthodoxall in all ſubſtanciall points of religion: yea admirable for their vvritings in queſtions tvvixt us and the papiſts. Diuerſe of vvhoſe anſvveres are applyed to M. D reaſons (vvhich he borrovved of the papiſts) and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not eaſely to be replyed to by him, nor departed from by us.
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:15958:29"/>In his ſecond Condition, he requireth more <hi>Chriſtian and modeſt dealing,</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in that book called the <hi>Chriſtian &amp; modeſt offer,</hi> which faith he, <hi>notwithstanding that title is full of odious Cenſures, proud &amp; ſcornefull ſpeaches, vnchriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; immodeſt provocations great bitternes &amp; gall &amp;c.</hi> Yf it ſhould be ſoe, which nether hath he ſhewed, nor can I acknowledge, yet lett the Chriſtian reader compare that their book, with this his preface, and I dout not but he will ſaie <hi>turpe est doctori &amp;c.</hi> it is a foul fault in a teacher, to be deeplier guil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty of the fault him ſelf, then the partie he blameth. I for my parte, when I read it, thought of the Philoſophers
<note n="(f)" place="margin">Diog. Laert: in Diogene</note> cenſuring and chec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king of ſuch as offred ſacrifyce for health, and at their very ſacrify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing did banquet riotouſly againſt health: &amp; of our regrators who have double waites &amp; balances, ſome for buying &amp; ſome for ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. The Lord giue us more charitie in our hearts then onely to upbrayd others with the want of it, &amp; not feel our owne want in the practyce. Thus are we come to his promiſſe, <hi>that he will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge his error,</hi> the which if it be aſwell performed as promy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, we maie ſaie to him as Cyprian to Cornelius, though he miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of the firſt <hi>degree of happines,</hi> which is, <hi>not to offend;</hi> yet it ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be well with him that he hath mett with <hi>the ſecond,</hi> vz. having don<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>amiſſe to acknowledge it. And ſhalbe gladd to acknowledge him for none of thoſe, who convinced of error, bluſh not to ſaye, <hi>haud ſcio an iſta veraſunt, fortaſsis non multum abſunt a veris, ſed tamen li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet ire contra.</hi> It maie be it is not vntrue that you ſaie: but yet I lik not to follovv it. I muſt goe againſt it. And to take M. D. by the hand, yf this anſwere ſatisfy him not, but ſhall ſeeme too light in compariſon of his ſermon, lett him laye open the vanitie &amp; bring the inſufficiencie therof to light, I dare promis in the name of the reſte, we will (as Ierom ſayd to Cteſiphon) rather revoak our er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, then perſiſte in a wronge ſentence. And thus are we come to his 4. &amp; laſte head: to wit, the concluſion with proteſtation: which
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:15958:30"/>is, <hi>that what he hath deliuered either in his preface or ſermon, is that which in his conſcience he is verely perſwaded to be the truth.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto what ſhall I ſaie? I would rather have thought, he had this once done that, which many others have often done before him; &amp; from the doing whereof the Fathers (as Ierom
<note n="(g)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jero<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Apol: pro lib. contra Iovin; Cap:</hi> 4.</note> noteth) the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in the heate of their contentions, were not alwaiſe free, <hi>non quod ſentiunt, ſed quod neceſſe eſt dicunt, aduerſus ea quae dicunt gentiles,</hi> that he had ſpoken, not what in his conſcience he thought to be the truth, but, <hi>quod neceſſe eſt dicere contra fratres,</hi> that which the cauſe he vndertooke neceſſarily drew him; to ſpeake againſt his brethren: but ſeing in charitie which beleeueth all things, I muſt herein credit him, I have no more to ſaye, but that his conſcience is blind, or was a ſleep when he wrote this ſermon, vvherein are contradictories, both which cannot be true. And ſoe with the lik proteſtation, &amp; commendation of him to the grace of God, I end with the words of Cypria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to Florentius:
<note n="(h)" place="margin">
                  <hi>lib.</hi> 4 <hi>epiſt.</hi> 9.</note> habes tu literas meas &amp; ego tuas, in die judicij ante tribunal Chriſti vtraeque recitabuntur. I have your vvritings both ſermon &amp; preface, you have my an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweres, (both according to the perſwaſion of our conſciences) &amp; both to be recited before the tribunall of Chriſte. The Lord grant, that knowing that terror of the Lord, we ſoe perſwad men, as we maie approve our ſelues to God &amp; the conſciences of his Children Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:15958:30"/>
            <head>Errata in the Preface.</head>
            <p>p. 3. l. 19 <hi>read,</hi> a doctrine. p 4. in marg. book. p. 11. l. 29. good, that ibid. l. 30. the middeſt. p. 12. l. 17. way then. p 13 l. 15 that we p. 17. l. 22. <hi>after</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trouerſy, <hi>adde</hi> then yong Divines for ſtudieng that controverſy, p. 20. l. 19 if he p: 28. l 10. upon any other occaſion ibid. l. 14. very caſe. p. 29. l. 26. ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> p. 30. l. 2. deprivations, degradations. p. 31. l. 10. amongſt us. p. 32 l. 22. an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtas rimulas p. 36. l. 20 loadeth p. 37. l. 9 <hi>put</hi> Lindwood <hi>in marg.</hi> ibid. l. 20. heavier p. 39 l. 6. knew not p. 43. l. 20 fall &amp; p 45. l. 2, velle ibid. l <hi>in marg.</hi> Baronius p. 46. l. 26. at p. 48. l. 4. firſt branch, p 49. l 28. aſſertions p. 50. l. 28 confidence p. 51. l. ult. not M D. p. 52. l. ult. Drones p. 54. l. 25. in caſe.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>In the reſt of the book.</head>
               <p>p. 3 l. 16 great p. 20 l. 19 becauſe p. 35 l 12 presbyters ibid. 29 Elders p 65 l. 20 here cited p. 66 l 4.4.5.6 or ibid. 10 great cities p. 67 l. 7 teſtimony of writers ibid. l. 33 Thirdly D Fulck, p 68 l. 1; Heron. ibid, l. 20 of the M p 69 l 23 5 Sections ibid. 27 draining it p. 70 l. 1 holds ibid. l. 4 overweening p. 71 l. 22 could the p ibid. l. 32 I miſtake ibid. l 34 in the end p. 72 l 32 I ſay ibid 34 I confes ib l. 35 I ſay p 75 l. 12 M. D. giveth p. 76 l 13 ouer Cities and D. p. 78 l. 3 if I ibid. l. 9 I trouble ib. l. 23 Apoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les p. 79 l. 1 I may ib. l. 19 policy ib l. 24 primitive p. 80 l. 3 towards ib. l. 33 therefore which p, 86 10 but to p, 88 16 ſtrongly p, 97 l. 32 are 2 l nes to much p. 106 l, 2 being loſt p, 111 l, 27 dioceſan p, 115 l. 22 not to the ib. l. 28 ſo ordered p, 117 l, 7 93 p, 119 l, 12 95 p, 124 l, 1 Sedulius ib, l, 2 Epiſcopus ib, l, 5 Medina ib, l, 9 presbyters p, 125 l, ult. in all the p, 133 l, 19 more cleanly p, 135 l, 13 this to the p, 146 19 we heard p. 14 8 l, 27 that word p, 149 l, 2 in office p, 153 l, 5 ſo it was p, 15 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> l, 29 conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded p, 160 l, 21 conſecration p 161 l, 29 Baſil, where he was p. 16 21, 23 shee ever.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
